<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Inuicta veritas. An answere, that by no maner of lawe, it maye be lawfull for the moste noble kinge of englande, kinge Henry the ayght to be diuorsed fro[m] the quenes grate, his lawful and very wyfe</title>
            <author>Abell, Thomas, d. 1540.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1532</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 209 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 71 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A19677</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 61</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S110723</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99846213</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99846213</idno>
            <idno type="VID">11164</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A19677)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 11164)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 20:29)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Inuicta veritas. An answere, that by no maner of lawe, it maye be lawfull for the moste noble kinge of englande, kinge Henry the ayght to be diuorsed fro[m] the quenes grate, his lawful and very wyfe</title>
                  <author>Abell, Thomas, d. 1540.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[144] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[M. de Keyser],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted at Luneberge [i.e. Antwerp] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>the yere of ower Lorde God. M. D. XXXII. in Maye.[1532]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Thomas Abell.</note>
                  <note>Authorship, actual publication place and printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-S⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Henry VIII, 1509-1547 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:11164:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11164:1"/>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> INVICTA VE<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>RITAS.</p>
            <p>¶ An anſwere, Th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at by no maner of lawe / it maye be lawfull for the moſte noble Kinge of englande / Kinge Henry the ayght to be diuorſed fro the quenes gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce / his lawful and very wyfe.</p>
            <p>Sette a parte Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten reader all blynde affeccion: and read this boke with iugement / conferringe it with the tother bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke agenſt which this is writen: and I doute not / but thou ſhalt ſtande on the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis parte / as a fauourer of the firme and inuincible Verite.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:11164:2"/>
            <head>AD LAVDEM TVAM DOMINE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Er folowith an anſwer / that I Tho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mas Abell prieſt haue made vnto a certain yngliſhe boke late put forthe and imprinted: which doith falſly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme and ſaye that it is againſte the law of God / and againſte the lawe of nature for a man to mary his brothers wife a widowe left wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thout yſſewe / and that the Pope hath no power to diſpence vpon ſuche mariage: the which ſaing you ſhal ſe declared and prouid falſe / more clerly &amp; mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re largely by holy ſcripture / by holy decrees / by d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>octours / and expounders of holy ſcripture / and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo by reaſon here within / than at the beginninge of my anſwer / And in lyk maner ye ſhal ſe this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſicion and ſayng declared and prouyd trew / that a criſten man may lefully mary his brothers wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owe left &amp;c. bothe by the lawe of God / and by the lawe of nature: and that the Pope hath power to diſpence vpon ſuche mariage: for thowghe at the beginninge of myn anſwere / I ſhewe ſufficiently the firſt ſaynge to be falſe / and this other laſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſicion and ſaynge to be trew: yet for bicauſe that I am compelled to folow the proceſſe of the yngly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhe boke which I anſwere to: I declare and proue the reherſid propoſicions more largely within th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is myne anſwere according as the occaſion is offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rd: the which if I had done alſo in the beginning I
<pb facs="tcp:11164:2"/> ſhuld haue / reherſed one thing and one profe many tymes / and ſo my anſwere wolde haue bene very tedious and longe.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or aſmuche as now of late ther be cer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tayn perſons that haue made a boke in Latyn and the ſame haue tranſlat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it again into Engliſhe / where they doo affirme and ſaye that a man to m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary his brothers wife a widowe / left without yſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we / is ſo vnleful and ſo againſte the law of God / and againſt the lawe of nature / that the Pope ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th no power to diſpence vpon ſuche mariages / w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hether they be made and contracte al redy / or els yet to be made or contracte: I am at this tyme co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mpellid and conſtrayned by my profeſſion and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſſe that I haue made vnto owr ſauiour criſte to anſwere vnto this vntrewe ſayng and to ſpeke ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aynſte it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt for bicauſe to ſaye and affirme th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at it is forbidden bothe by the lawe of God a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d by the law of nature for a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to mary his brothers wife a widow &amp;c and that the Pope can in no wiſe diſp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence vpon ſuche mariage made / or yet to be made is very falſe and vntrew: and alſo gret a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d high b<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſphemy to god is law and to almighty God him ſelf as I ſhal ſhew ye here after</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:11164:3"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Nd ſecondly I am compellid and bou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nde to ſpeke againſt this propoſicion and ſayng / for to admonyſhe and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue my neighbour knowleg of this vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trew opynion that is nowe ſet owt in printe and goith a brode / to aduertyſe hym to take hede of this ſaynge and to giue in no wiſe credence vnto it / for it is no ſmal daungere to mens ſowles to beleue this falſe ſayng and gret blaſphemy / the which vngraciouſe perſons haue / and in their bok<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es do coloure and ornate with myche rethorike and eloquent wordis to thentent that their falſe propo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſicions &amp; ſayngis ſhuld be the ſoner beleuyd &amp; acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pte of the reders. And ſo thus for theſe cauſes I am compellid to anſwere and ſpeke againſt this be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore reherſhed boke / in the which anſwere I wil w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ith the aſſiſtence &amp; helpe of almyghty God ſhew ye how y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this propoſicion &amp; ſaynge is falſe &amp; highe blaſphemy to almyghty God to affirme &amp; ſaye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is forbiden &amp; to be againſt the law of God / &amp; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the law of nature y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> eny man ſhuld mary h<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is brothers wyfe a widowe / lefte &amp;c: and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe hath no power to diſpence vppon ſuche maria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis whether that they be contracte al redy / or els yet to be made &amp; contracte / &amp; I wil alſo here ſhewe ye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this is trew y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a man may by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law of God a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law of nature lefully mary his brothers wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe a widowe left with out yſſewe / and that the Po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pe hath power to diſpence vppon ſuche mariages and to licence a man ſo to mary.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:11164:3"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hre thinges principally I note that the perſons the which haue ſetforth their boke do ſaye. The firſt is this. In the preface of their boke they ſay that the vniuerſites haue confirmed their determinacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leuitical laws by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che it is forbiden that eny man ſhulde mary y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe of his brother departed without children. The ſeconde principall pointe and their ſaynge is write<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the forſaid preface the which is this. That it is forbiden bothe by the law of God and by the lawe of nature that any Criſten man ſhulde mary the wife of his brother dyinge without children. The thyrde principal pointe and ſayng is writen in the ſame preface ioyned vnto the ſecond ſayng whiche is this / that the Pope hath no pow<hi rend="sup">r</hi> to diſpence v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon eny ſuche mariagis whether they be contracte all redy or els yet to be contracte. Now to their fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte ſayng. where they write that the vniuerſites haue confirmed their determinacions vppon thes leuitical lawes by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which yt is fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>biden that eny man ſhuld mary the wife of his brother departed without children. Beholde here I praye ye vppon how goodly and ſubſtanciall a grounde thies perſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons do ſay y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vniuerſites haue buylded &amp; ſet ther determinacions. thei ſay vpon the leuitical lawes by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which it is forbiden y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> any man ſhuld mary y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wife of his broth<hi rend="sup">r</hi> departed without children: whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leuitical law ther is no ſuch mariagis for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may perceue &amp; vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loke upon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11164:4"/> leuitical lawes / &amp; alſo as ye ſhal ſe it more large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly declared here after / &amp; by this alſo ye may perce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue what thies vniuerſites haue determined / that is in dede no thinge but a propoſicion the which ys very falſe euen lyke as the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> grounde is that they haue bilded their determinacions vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Now to the ſecond pointe principal / and ſaynge of thies perſons where as they ſaye that it is forbiden bothe by the law of God and by the law of nature that eny cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten man ſhulde mary the wife of his brother dep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arted without children: this is likewiſe falce / Firſt it is not againſt the lawe of God: for in the law of God / God him ſelf by his ſeruant Moyſes dide commaunde and that vpon greate payne that eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry man of the Iues ſhuld mary his brothers wife a widowe left &amp;c. as it is playnly expreſſed in the olde lawe / nor ſuche mariagis be not forbiden in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> new law / as ye ſhal ſe it euidently proued:<note place="margin">Deute. xxv.</note> wherfor it is not againſt the law of God for a man to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry his brothers wife a widow. nor eny ſuche mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age in none of the lawes be forbiden / alſo for a man to mary his brothers wife a widow / is not forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en by the lawe of nature.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">gen. xx</note>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt for bycauſe the holy patriarke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham maried his owne ſiſter Sara and we maye not thinke and ſaye th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at ſo holy a man wolde wetingely do ſo greuouſe a ſyn as to breke the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we of nature / and to continew ſtill in the ſame of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence:
<pb facs="tcp:11164:4"/> wherfor it is not againſt the law of nature f<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or a man to mary his brothers wyfe a widowe &amp;c. If it be not forbiden by the law of nature for a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to mary his ſiſter / than is it not forbiden that a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal mary his brothers wife a widowe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lſo Ierome ſaith that at the tyme that Abraham maryd his ſiſter / <note place="margin">In que<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtionib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us heb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raicis ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uper ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſim.</note> ſuche mariage was not forbiden by the law / and Ierome therfor excuſith the Patriarke Abraham alſo the Patriarche Iuda maryed his ſecond ſone to his doughter in law Thamar / for by cauſe hir firſte huſbande Iudas his ſone died withowt yſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we / they and alſo the ſame Patriarke after the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the of his ſecunde ſone Thamars ſecunde huſba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nde promyſed hir his thirde ſone / and alſo this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly man Iuda commaundid his ſeconde ſone to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry his brothers wife a widow / <note place="margin">Geneſ. xxxviij</note> the which he wolde not haue commaundid / if it had bene againſt the l<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aw of nature / wherfor ye may ſe that it is not ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ainſt the law of nature for a man to mary his bro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thers wife a widow / when that theis holy patriar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes did in the tyme of the lawe of nature vſe ſuche mariages &amp; did co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maund their childern ſo to mary</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lſo holy Criſoſtome ſaith that whan Iuda the Patriarke co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>did his ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nde ſone to take and mary his broth<hi rend="sup">r</hi>s wife Thamar / <note place="margin">ſuꝑ ge. ho. lxij.</note> &amp; ſo to ſtyre vp ſeid a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d procure by hyr yſſewe vnto his brot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:11164:5"/> that was ded: thus ſaith Criſoſtom did Iuda co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maund bi y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law &amp; than the<hi rend="sup">r</hi> was no other lawe but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law of natu<hi rend="sup">r</hi> or els cuſtoms laudable &amp; poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical gro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded in the law of natu<hi rend="sup">r</hi> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which this w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as one y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhuld mary his brothers wife a w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>idow &amp;c. for els the Patriarche iuda wold not haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundid his ſone ſo to haue maryd / <note place="margin">Geneſ. xxxviij</note> alſo this d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oith appere euidently by iudas wordes / for he conf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſid &amp; grauntid y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he had offendid &amp; done wrong to Thamar bycauſe he had not maryed his thyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de ſone vnto hir / &amp; if y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it had be againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law of n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ature for a man to mary his brothers wife a wido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we &amp;c. than Iuda hade done no wronge to Tham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he did <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot mary his thirde ſone vnto hir / but for aſmuche as y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was not agaynſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law of na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture / therfor Iuda did co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he did Thamar w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronge for bycauſe he had not maried his thirde ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne vnto hir / according vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law / ſo now ye may ſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is not againſte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe of nature for a man to mary his brothers wife a widowe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irthermore for a man to mary his br<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>others wife a widow &amp;c. can not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the law of nature / for almyg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hty God did neuer commaund eny m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ner of people to obſerue and kepe th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at thinge continually and vppon a gret payne th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at ſhuld be agaynſt the law of nature / for that w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ere euyl of it ſelf / <note place="margin">Ec. xv</note> &amp; therfor no ſoche thing almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God did co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d as it is writen / nemini ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dauit
<pb facs="tcp:11164:5"/> impie agere / but almyghty did commaunde the Iwes to marye alwayes their brothers wifis left without yſſew: and that onder a gret payne / And this comaundement he wold haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pte durynge the tyme of that lawe / wherfore yow may ſee euidently that ſuche mariages can not be agaynſt the law of nature / this argument doithe conclude / it can not be denyed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Did ſay in the firſt principall propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of this argument / that almygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God dide neuer commaunde enny maner of parſon to obſerue and kepe that thynge contynewally and that vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a gret payne which ſhuld be againſt the law of nature / this I did ſaye to take awaye certain ob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ieccions as this / that almyghty God did comm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunde Abraham to kyl his ſoon that was innoc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent / but yet almyghty God did not commaunde euery man ſo to doo continually: and likewiſe tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wgh almyghty God did commaunde the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of the people of Iſrael to borowe plate of the Egyptians and to carye it away with them / yet almighty God did not commaunde the people of Iſrael to doo ſo continually nor yet he did not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde them ſo to do vppon a payne: but as I ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue ſaide / almyghty God commaunded the people of Iſrael to mary always their brothers wifes wi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dows lefte without yſſew / and that vppon a gret paine / wherfor I ſaye that ſuche mariagis cannot
<pb facs="tcp:11164:6"/> be againſt the law of nature: parauenture yet ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m perſones will ſaye that this commaundemente of almyghty God that bownd the Iues to mary ther brothers wifis widows &amp;c / was no law but a licence and a diſpenſacion that almyghty God ga<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue vnto the Iues / wherby they myght vſe ſuche mariages / as almighty God did before the lawe diſpence with Iacob to mary .ij. ſiſters / and hade theym both wifes at ons / And alſo in the tyme of the lawe he did diſpence withe certayne kyngis to haue .ij. wifes at ons / or mo / To this I anſwer th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us / that thowghe almyghty God did ſuffre ſuche mariage before the law / and in the tyme of the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we that men hade mo wifes at ons then one / yet he neuer commaundid that the Iues ſhuld take moo wifes than one at ons / nor yet co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundid the plu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ralite of wifes vppon a payne / alſo almighty god ſufferd the Iues to forſake ther wifes by the lib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell of repudiacion / and likewiſe the Iues to vſe vſury / but yet this / nor the other he did neuer com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maunde to be kepte as a law &amp; that vppon a grete payne: but almyghty God did commaunde all the Iues alwayes to marye theyr brothers wifis wedowes lefte without yſſew / and that vnder a grete payne / wherfor this commaundement was no diſpenſacion / but a playne lawe / and thus yow maye ſee that ſuche mariagis can not be ageynſte the lawe of nature.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:11164:6"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow to the thirde pointe and principa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ll ſayinge of theis perſones: wheras thei affirme that the Pope hath no po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to diſpence vppon mariagis ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de bitwixt the brother and the brothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rs wife widowe left without yſſew / nor yet power to diſpence vppon ſuche mariage to be made. Th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is ſaynge is falſe lykewiſe as the other before: ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che mariage is not forbiden nether in the olde la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we nor in the newe lawe as yow haue herde befo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re / and the ſame you ſhal ſe here aftyr more large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly declared and prouid where as I brynge yn the doctours myndes ageynſt thies deceyuers opyni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: wherfore now I ſaye that this ys falſe to ſay and affirme that the Pope haith no power to lic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence the brother to mary the brothers wife a wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owe left without yſſewe: for it is forbiden that a man maye mary withe her that is ioynyd to hym in the firſt degre of lateral affynyte but onely by the lawe and ordinaunce of the churche as you ſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al here aftir ſe prouyd by the myndis of grete and excellente lernyde men / And the Pope hathe po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to dyſpence againſt the prohibicion of his ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne lawes onely / this can no man deny wherfore yt is falſe to affirme and ſaye that the Pope hathe no power to licence a man to marye his brothers wife a widowe lefte with owt yſſewe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>NOw here yow haue herde howe that thies perſones ſayngis and opinion ys falſe wh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iche
<pb facs="tcp:11164:7"/> ys this: that it is agaynſte the lawe of God and againſt the lawe of nature for a man to mary his brothers wife a widowe left without yſſewe / and that the Pope hathe no power to diſpence vp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pon ſuche mariage: by the which falſhed ye may perceyue how that this propoſicion ys trew / that a man may lefully by the law of God and by the lawe of nature mary his brothers wife a widow lefte without yſſew / and that the Pope haithe p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ower to diſpence vppon ſuche mariage. Firſt ye haue ſene that ſuche mariage ys not againſte the lawe of nature. Alſo yowe haue harde howe that ſuche mariage ys not forbiden by the olde lawe / but in the olde lawe ſuche mariagis were expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly commaundid and ſo by the lawe a man myght lefully mary his brothers wife a widowe &amp;c.<note place="margin">Mat. xxij</note> And alſo ſuche mariage owr ſauyour Criſte did appro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bate in the newe lawe as yt ys open where as the ſaduceys came to owre ſauiowre Chriſte and ſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ewid hym howe that there was a woman withe theme that hade maryde ſeuyn Brothern one aft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er a nothers dethe / the whiche mariage owr ſaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oure Chriſte did not reproue nor ſpeke agaynſte theym / but ſuerly yf ſuche mariage had bene agay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nſte the lawe of nature and agaynſte Chriſtis la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we / than wolde owr ſauiour Chriſte haue ſpoken agaynſte ſuche mariage like as he ſpake agayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte the libell of repudiacion wherby the Iues did vſe to refuſe theyr wifes and mary other when t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hey were a lyue / and alſo the ſame wifes ſo refuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yde
<pb facs="tcp:11164:7"/> and put awaye did take and mary other men their firſte huſbandes beynge a lyue / and for aſm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uche as theys manner of mariages were vnlef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ull and agaynſte the lawe of nature owre ſauiou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re Criſte did reproue theyme as he dide reproue othere imperfeccions that the Iues vſide in their law, for owre ſauioure Chriſte came to fulfill the lawe withe perfeccion / and ſo for aſmuche as he did not reproue mariage betwene the brother and t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>he brothers wife a widowe lefte without yſſewe ſeynge that owre ſauioure hade occaſion offeryd to ſpeke vpon ſuche mariage / yt folowith that he di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de alow and approbate ſuche mariage / Parauent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ure yet ſum perſons will ſaye that thowgh owre ſauioure Criſte did not ſpeke agaynſte mariage betwene the brother and the brothers wife wido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we &amp;c. yet it doith not folowe / that he did approb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate ſuche mariage: for owre ſauioure dide not forb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>id the father to mary withe the doughter / and yet it doith not folowe that he did approbate that the father myght lefully mary his doughter / yf this were trewe that owre ſauioure did not forbide the father to mary with his dowghter the whiche ys falſe / yet than this reaſon ys not lyke the other. Firſt by cauſe that mariage betwene the fath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the doughter ys expreſly forbiden bi the law of nature by the olde law and by the newe lawe / and ſo is not mariage betwene the brother and the brothers wife / and ſecundarily for by cauſe ther was no occaſion offerde / vnto owre ſaviowre
<pb facs="tcp:11164:8"/> Criſte to approbate or to haue reprovid mariage betwene the father and the doughter / as ther was in the other mariage / but yf the Iues had comen vnto our ſauyour Criſte and ſhewed hym howe ther was a man that had maried .ij. or thre of hys owne doughters / one after the dethe of an other than he wold haue ſpoken ageynſte ſuche maria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge by cauſe that ſuche is yll / and vnlefull: but for aſmuche as mariage betwene the brother / and the brothers wife widow &amp;c / ys good and lefull by the lawe of Nature / and by the lawe of gode: ower ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uioure Chriſte did approbate ſuche mariage / No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we than ſeynge that mariage betwene the broth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and the brothers wife is lefull by the law of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and commaundide in the olde lawe and appr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obate bi owr ſauiour Criſt / than it folowithe that ſuche mariage is forbiden onely / by the ordinau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nce and lawe of the churche / And the pope hathe power to licens againſte that ordinaunce / and ſo conſequently he hath power to diſpence vpon ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>he mariage / Thus now you haue ſomewhat her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de thies deceyuers opinion prouid falſe / and howe that this ys trew / that a man maye by the lawe of God / and by the lawe of nature mary his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wife a widowe lefte with owte yſſewe / and that the Pope hathe power to diſpence vppon ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>he mariage. yet for aſmich as theſe diſceuers ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue in their boke that I make anſwere vnto many clokyde reaſons with eloquent and rethorik ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mys and many falſe argumentis / and grete lyes
<pb facs="tcp:11164:8"/> and muche blaſphemy to Gode coueryd withe the ſame maner of cloth: I will diſcover yow ſome of their errors to thentent that you ſhal not be dece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid nor beleue their falſe ſaynges / but yet I ſaye that I wil diſcouer and reherſe yowe but ſome of theyr errors: fore yf I wold tarye to reherſe you all I ſhuld be compellid to make a grete boke / and th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfor I wil not take that way: but rather towche / and ſpeke of ſome: and by them yowe maye perceue the reſidewe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the firſte chapiter of theyr boke th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ey ſaye that before the flowde the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſet all their myndes at al tymes to nawghtines and ſyn / in ſo muche that they toke theym wifis at adauenturs whom ſo euer they hade choſen ſparinge nor forbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe no maner of degre of affinite or kindered / th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is is ther ſaynge / groundinge them of this ſcript<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ure.<note place="margin">Ge. vi.</note> Videntes filij dei filias hominum quod eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent pulchre / acceperunt ſibi vyores ex omnibus quas elegerant. This ys the ſence of this ſcript<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ure / the childern of God ſeynge the doughters of men that they were beauteful and fayre / they cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe of al theym to their wifis ſuche as liked them And theis perſones write / that the men toke the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wifes at adauentures whome ſo euer thei hade ch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſen ſparinge nor forberinge no maner of degre of affinite or kindrede / And this ſaynge can no wiſe be takyn of the reherſed ſcripture / but rather
<pb facs="tcp:11164:9"/> by the ſame ſcripture it folowithe that thies perſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſaye falſe / fore the Scripture ſaithe that the childern / and the ſones of God / ſeynge the doug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hters of men fayer and beautiful / toke of them w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ifes ſuche as liked them / and it folowith that thei maried not with their mothers nor their own ſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers / nor their owne auntis / for they maryed withe the doughters of men whiche were nether their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wne mothers / nor their ſiſters / nor theyr auntes / and therfor it is falſe to ſaye that the people mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ied them wifes forberyng nor ſparinge no maner of degre of affinite or kindred / this error ys writen in the .xvi. leyffe of theyr boke.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lſo in the ſame firſt chapiter of theyr boke in the .xvij. and .xviij. leyffe they ſaye that almighty God did co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mmaunde Moyſes to preſcribe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his people laws of matrimony th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at ſhuld be conformable and agreynge with hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtye and ſhamefaſtnes natural / and to forbide ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che mariages that be foule of them ſelf / and haue diſhoneſtye in them / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d al this they ſay was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundid in the leuitical boke / in the .xviij. chapit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er / And amonge the mariages that they ſaye be ther forbiden ys forbyden mariage betwene the b<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rother and the brothers wife widow left without yſſewe / this thies perſones ſpeake of / or elles all that they ſaye is no thing for their purpoſe / whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rfore to this ſaynge I anſwere thus / Firſte in the
<pb facs="tcp:11164:9"/> xviij. chapiter of the leuitical boke is not forbyden that a man may not mary his brothers wife a w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>idowe left without yſſew / no nor yet ſuche maria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges are not forbiden in no Place of the hole lawe / but rather where as Moyſes did declare the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiticall lawe / ye and all the hole law / that he had writen before / he ſhewid vnto the people how th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at almyghty God had ordyned and commaund<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>id that euery one of the Iues ſhuld mary always his brothers wife a widowe lefte with out yſſewe as yt ys manifeſte in the boke of the deuteronomi wherfore yow maye euidently ſe that in the .xviij chapiter of the Leuyticall lawe yt was not forby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den that a man myght not mary his brothers wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe a widowe lefte withe owte yſſewe / and alſo the prohibicione in the Leuiticall lawe in the .xviij.<note place="margin">Chap. xxv</note> Chapiter can not be al vnderſtand that they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide mariage withe all ſuche perſons as be ther namyd. For there it ys forbyden that a man may goo to a woman when that ſhe hathe a paſſion the whiche they call hyr flowers / And yet yet ys eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent that a man maye mary a woman when that ſhe hath theym / And lykewiſe that a woman m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ayelefully mary when that ſhe hath them. whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rfore yow may ſee that the prohibicions that be yn the .xviij. chapiter can not al be vnderſtond to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid mariage withe al ſuche perſons that be ther namyd / But yet parauenture thies falſe deceyu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers that hath made the boke that I anſwere now to / wil ſaye that in the .xviij. chapiter of the Leui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall
<pb facs="tcp:11164:10"/> ys forbiden that a man maye not mary h<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is brothers wife. To this I anſwere that yf t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hey will take that prohibicion to forbide Maria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge betwene the brother and the brothers wife / and not for the abuſing of the brothers wife. Th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an it is thus vnderſtand / that no man maye mary his brothers wife while his brother is a lyve. T<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hus ſaith thies perſones great doctor Peter de P<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alude expowndinge the .xviij. chapiter of the leui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tical boke / and ſo doith other doctors ſaye as yow ſhal ſee here after / and lykewiſe ſayth ſayncte A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uguſtyne expowndinge the .xviij. Chapiter of the leuitical boke that ther it is forbyden that a man may not mary his brothers wife while that hyr huſbande is a lyue / nor a man maye not mary his brothers wife that was refuſed and repudiate of hir huſband / nor yet a man maye not mary hys brothers wife a widowe hauinge yſſew bi hyr fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte huſband / But now by this reherſed prohibici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on nor by no other ys forbiden that a man may not mary his brothers wife a widowe lefte withoute yſſewe / yet further more you ſhal vnderſtande th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at the leuiticall prohibicions can not al be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande to forbyde mariage betwene al thoſe perſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that be there expreſſed / as to forbide that the brother may not mary with the ſiſter / or that the brother may not mary with the brothers wife / for yf mariage betwene thies perſons were forbyden there / than it ſhal folowe that the Egiptians and the canoneis were not poluted in al thies thinges
<pb facs="tcp:11164:10"/> that be called ther abominacions the whiche is pl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aynly agaynſte the texte: wherfore the prohibici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons can not be al vnderſtande to forbide mariage betwene all thos perſons that be ther namyd / th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at this ſhulde folowe it is euident: for kynge Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro did beleve that Sara was not Abra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s wif / for as muche as Abraham ſayde that ſhe was his ſiſter and the cauſe why Pharo did ſo beleue was this for as muche as in egipte the people did not mary their ſiſters / and therfor when that Abraham ſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ewid kinge Pharo that Sara was his ſiſter / he b<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elevid that ſhe was not his wife as the proceſſe in the texte doith euidently ſhewe / And likewiſe for bycauſe Abraham ſaide in the contre of Canan to kinge Abymelech that Sara his wife was his ſiſter the kinge Abymelech did beleue that Sara was not Abrahams wife / for as myche as in that contre they dide not vſe to mary ther ſiſters.<note place="margin">gen. xii</note> and al this that the Egiptians and the Cananeis did not vſe to mary ther ſiſters / doithe thies deceyve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rs affirme in the .cxj.<note place="margin">gen. xx</note> leife of ther boke ſpeking t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>her of Abraham and his wife. nowe than by this the trewth and ther graunte alſo / it folowith / th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at the prohibicions leuiticall can not be all vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand of forbiddinge of mariage / when that the Cananeis did not vſe to mary ther ſiſters as th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ies deceyuers do graunte them ſelfe / And th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an it folowith ſtill / that if the Egypcions &amp; Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naneis did not vſe to mary their owne ſiſters that than they dyde not vſe to mary ther mothers nor
<pb facs="tcp:11164:11"/> their auntis nor their mothers in lawe and ſo fort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>he / for yf the Egipcians did iuge to be ageynſt ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſte and reaſon to mary their ſiſters / and therfor they did abſtayne for to mary them / than thei muſt nedes iuge / that it is more agaynſte reaſon and honeſte / for to mary with ther mothers / with m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>others in lawe / with ther fathers ſiſters / and w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ithe ther mothers ſiſters / and ſo they did therfore myche more abſtayne to mary with them / This re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>aſon can no man deny / wherfore yowe maye ſee by thies argumentis foundid in theyr owne ſaynge that the leuiticall prohibicions can not be all vnd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erſtond that they forbide mariage betwene al the perſons that be namyd in the .xviij. chapiter of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leuitical boke / &amp; ſo now ye may ſe euidently that al their grounde / and fundacion is falſe: for in that ch<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>apiter they founde falſly there falſe opinion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lſo in the ſame firſt chapiter of power boke in the .xix. leyfe: thes perſons ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ye / that what man hathe maryed his brothers wife / the whiche is vnderſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nde of a widowe left without yſſew / ſhuld be Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of all the people not onely to haue contempn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yd and diſpiced God the which hath withe ſo gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at mageſty commaundid the contrary / but alſo to haue offendid by infectinge and corruptinge the maners of the people by ſuche myſchevous exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to haue done ageinſt the law of nature. this is their ſayng the which I beſeche yow to note &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rke wel. Firſt they ſay that almighty God hathe
<pb facs="tcp:11164:11"/> with greate mageſte commaundid the contrary to this that a man may lefully mary his brothers wife a widow left without yſſew / but this I wold ſe them ſhew / and where: but that thei can not do nor yet no man: for almyghty God neuer comm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aundid the contrary / but he did expreſly commau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nde that a man ſhuld mary his brothers wife a w<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>idow left without yſſew / beſide this thes perſons do greatly blaſpheme almyghty God in their ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ng / for yf the people ſhuld iuge hym that hath m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aryed his brothers wife a widow &amp;c. to diſpiſe and diſpleaſe almyghty god: than ſhuld the people iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge that almyghty God co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundid the Iwes to contemne him and to diſpiſe him: for almighty god as I ſhewed yow / commaundid the Iwes to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ther brothers wifes / widows &amp;ce. Moreouer yf the people ſhuld Iuge him that hath maryed hys brothers wife a widow &amp;cet. to offend and infecte &amp; to corrupte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maners of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people by ſuche myſche<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uous example / &amp; to haue doon againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law of n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ature / tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhuld y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people iuge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> almighty god did co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maund y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iues to offend to infecte / &amp; to corrupte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maners of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people / &amp; alſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundid y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iues to giue miſcheuous example / &amp; to do agenſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law of nature / for it was almighty God y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundid them to mary ther broth<hi rend="sup">r</hi>s wifis widows &amp;ce. &amp; thꝰ ye may now ſe howe thies ꝑſons blaſpheme alm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yghty god &amp; his holy law: for they ſaye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> for a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to mary his broth<hi rend="sup">r</hi>s wif a widow &amp;c. ys abominable &amp; infection &amp; a corruption of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maners of the people
<pb facs="tcp:11164:12"/> a myſchevous example and a breking of the law of nature / and yet thei can not deny but that alm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yghty God did commaunde ſuche mariagis / and ſo they laye al this abhominacion vpon almygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God whiche is great diſpiſynge and blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my vnto hym.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Tem moreouer in the .xx. leife of the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ir boke thies perſons ſaye ouer and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide al this / Conſyder with hou great ſtrenght and weight of wordis and w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ith how great care and thowght God in decerning thes lawes doith ofen reherſe / ſayng yt is not for a man / yt ys fowlnes yt ys myſcheu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes / yt ys curſidnes / yt ys abominacyon / yt ys not to be ſpoken / yt is not leful / yt ys agaynſt the lawes of God / breuely yt ys fylthy and ſclander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ows that a man ſhuld do any ſuche thinge / Here now agayne thes perſones do hiely blaſpheme al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myghty god: for yf that mariage betwene the bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and the brothers wife / be ſo yl and ſo abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable as here they ſaye it ys / than they ſaye that almyghty God did command that thinge that ys meate for no man to doo / that is to ſaye fowlnes / that thynge that ys myſcheuous / curſednes / abh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ominacion / yt is not to be ſpoken / it is not leful / it ys ageynſt the very lawes of God / brevely yt ys filthy and ſclanderous that a man ſhulde do any ſuche thinge / for it was almyghty God that did commaunde that men ſhulde mary ther brothers
<pb facs="tcp:11164:12"/> wifes widows lefte with out yſſew. The whiche mariages thies perſons call abhominacion / myſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheuouſnes and ſclanderouſnes &amp;cet. For of ſuche mariage thes perſons ſpeke / Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider yow here w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ith how great ſtrenght and weight of wordie thes vngracius perſons do Blaſpheme almyghty god thay call hym the auctor and the commaunder of abhominacion of filthynes / and of curſidnes &amp;cet. who euer herd ſo great blaſphemy as ys this?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Owe where as before they ſayd that almyghty God in decerninge the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes ſpeketh with great ſtrenght and weight of wordes yt ys trew he did ſo for he ſpeaketh agaynſt the greate vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and abhominable lyuynge that the Egipcians and the Cananeis vſid / but let thies perſones ſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ewe where almyghty God doith ſpeake with gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at ſtrength and weight of wordes ageynſt maria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge betwene the brother and the brothers wife a w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>idow lefte without yſſew. Agaynſte ſuche maria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge almyghty God did neuer ſpeke but he did com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde expreſly ſuche mariage.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Nd yet thes falſe decevers do apply the ſpekinge of almyghty God / w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here he reprouid and ſpake agaynſt the greate ſyns of abhominable ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge of the Egypcians and the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanes / to be ageynſt the mariage betwene the bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:11164:13"/> and the brothers wife / a widowe lefte withe out yſſewe / and yt is no thinge ſo / wherfor yowe muſte note and marke wel thies perſones ſaynge for they doo not care how falſly they ſaye / nor yet how faſely they apply goddis ſayng and holy ſcr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ipture nor other mens ſaynge / ſo that they make ſuche ſaynges to apere for their falſe purpoſe / alſo you ſhall ſe them bringe in many thinges that pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rteyne no thynge to this / for to ſhew that it ys for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biden by the law of God and by the lawe of natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re for a man to marye hys brothers wife a widow left without yſſewe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Nd yow muſt note that in the olde lawe all that euer is ſpoken withe greate ſtrength and weyghte of wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des and forbidden and callid curſyd and abhominable and fylthynes / ys not thinges that be forbiden by the lawe of natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re / <note place="margin">Leui. xi</note> nor they be not ſo callid by cauſe they be yll of t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hem ſelf / for fyſſhe that hath no ſcales a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſinnes as elys and conger were callid abhominable for to ete / and yete it was not ageynſte the lawe of natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re for a man to ete elys and counger / <note place="margin">Leui. xi</note> Alſo all that crepith vppon the grounde was forbidden to ete in the olde law / and was callid abhominable / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d yet to ete ſnailles ys not agaynſt the lawe of nature / for ſnaillis be good and holſome and be eten in many placis / and ſo lykewiſe / yf a woman ſhulde haue worne a mans germent ſhe hade done abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable
<pb facs="tcp:11164:13"/> in the olde law / and for abominacion yt was forbidden / and yet yt was not agaynſte the lawe of nature. And ſo were thinges in that lawe callyd filthy and vnclenly and forbidden / and yet they were not againſt the lawe of nature / <note place="margin">leu. xv</note> as to t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouche caren of certayn beſtes / and many other thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nges were forbidden as fylthynes and foule thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges / and finally you muſt note that the great and greuous punyſhementis that were thretenyd yn the olde law / were not always thretenyd for bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge of the lawe of nature / as the childe that w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as not circumciſyd was thretened that he ſhulde periſhe from the middeſt of the people / and yet a childe that is not circumciſyd / doith not offende a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt the lawe of nature And yet beſide all this ye muſt note that the ſame thinge that was one againſt the lawe of nature / ys always againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe of nature / for the lawe of nature doith neuer moue nor altere hyr ſelf in no maner of tyme ſens Adam fell.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irthermore ye muſt marke and note that ſayncte Ierome ſaith in the Pr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ologe vppon Oſeas that almyghty God doith commaunde no thing but that which ys honeſte / nor almygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunding vnhoneſte thingis doith not make them honeſt ſuche as be fowle of them ſelf: w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herfor by this it folowith y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> for a man to mary his brothers wif a widow / was neu<hi rend="sup">r</hi> foule nor euyl of
<pb facs="tcp:11164:14"/> it ſelf / for than it coulde neuer haue bene good tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wghe almyghty god had commaundid yt neuer ſo muche. But almyghty God did commaunde ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>he mariage / wherfore ſuche mariage can not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt the law of nature / So nowe theſe fewe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wlys yow muſt take / and they ſhal helpe yowe to perceue the falſite of thies deceyuers.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow where as theſe deceyuers in the xx. ſeife of their boke ſay / forſoith yf a man will waye well and examine th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſe forſaid thinges religiouſly and wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th goode conſciens and ſo as they ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght to be / how can he but approue the trewth &amp; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the concluſions and determinacions of thies vniuerſites &amp; thinke certaynly that yt is forbiden both by the law of God and by the lawe of nature that a Chriſten man ſhuld mary his brothers w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ife a widowe? this is theſe perſons ſayng. To the whiche thus I anſwere / forſoith yf a man wil w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ay wel this caſe of matrimony / yf a Criſten man may mary his brothers wife a widow lefte withe out yſſew / and examyn yt with good conſciens as it owght to be / how ſhulde he not ſtreyght waye reproue and diſalowe the concluſions and determi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nations of thies vniuerſites that ſaye the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry / and to think certaynly that it is nether againſt the lawe of God nor againſt the law of nature for a Chriſten man to mary his Brothers wife a wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe &amp; cetera. This ſhal euery lernyd man that
<pb facs="tcp:11164:14"/> haith good conſciens iuge to be trewe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Oreouer where as thies deceyuers in the .xxi. leife of their boke ſaye that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſonnis of Cayn the whiche were drou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wnyd in Noys flowid / they were ſo pu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyſhed by cauſe they did foully abuſe theyr ſiſters and theyr brothers wifes / wherfore theſe perſons wold conclude that it is againſt the lawe of God and agaynſt the law of nature for a man to mary his Brothers wife a widow &amp;c. Here yow maye ſee a goodly Argument. Cayn ſonnys did fowly abuſe theyr ſiſters and theyr brothers wifes / wherfore yt is ageynſt the lawe of God a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d agaynſt the lawe of nature for a man to mary his brothers wife a widowe &amp;cet. What ſhuld a man ſaye to ſo lewid an Argument? but as the concluſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion is manifeſte falſe / ſo is all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the makers of the argument go abowt to proue.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lſo where as they ſaye in the ſame leif of theyr boke / Here ye maye ſee before yower eyes the holy lawes of God / here yow maye ſee the lyuely Prophecyes and the wordes of exce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge vertue and ſtrength &amp;c. And anone after they ſaye / forſoith it be comyth a Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten herte more to regard the wordes of God and his auctorite / whiche doith forbide and ſo hathe in abhominacion / ſo doith punyſhe and reuenge ſuche matrim
<pb facs="tcp:11164:15"/> mary his ſtepmother / wherfor yt is forbiden by t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>he lawe of God and by the lawe of nature that a man ſhulde mary his Brothers wife a widowe le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fte without yſſew / the maior of this argument is falſe / the whiche is this. That yt is forbiden yn y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame place of the lawe for a man to mary his ſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pmother where yt is forbidden for a man to mary his brothers wife a widowe &amp;ce. This propoſicion I ſaye is falſe: for yt is not forbidden in all the ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> lawe for a man to mary his brothers wife a wido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we left without yſſew. and ſo therfore the wordes of ſaynte polle helpith nothinge for thies perſons Purpoſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Nd alſo ſuche mariage and fornication that the Apoſtle doith here reproue / ys not ſpoken of in the Leuitical prohibici<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on: for this yonge man that had mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his mother in lawe / did take hyr from his fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>her: and ſo maryed hyr / his father beyng a lyue / as the wordes of ſayncte Poll a fore reherſed do ſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ewe / and therfore ſayncte Poll did not grounde h<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ym in the Leuiticall lawe when that he rebwl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed this Coryntheane for mariyng of his fathers wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe. That the father was a lyue of the Corynthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ane that maryed his mother in law / it ſemyth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo by thies wordes of the Apoſtle where he ſaithe ther is not ſuche fornication herde of amonge the gentiles / and ſayncte Poll beynge ſo well lernyd as he was knewe very wel that the Gentils had
<pb facs="tcp:11164:15"/> ſum tyme abuſyd theyr fathers wifes / alſo he k<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newe that the Iues had abuſyd their fathers wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fes bothe before the lawe and in the lawe: before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law Ruben abuſyd his fathers wife / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſo did A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bſalon in the lawe abuſe his fathers wifes / therf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ore this offence that this Coryntheane did was more than for to lye withe his fathers wife / or ellis ſaincte Poll wold not haue callid yt ſuche / &amp; ſo greuous fornication as hath not ben hard of / a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the gentiles. But for a man to take awaye his fathers wife from hym and openly mary hyr and ſo kepe hyr ſtill / ſuche maner of fornication h<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ath not ben herd of amonge the gentilz: and for by cauſe this Coryntheane had done ſo / therfore the holy Apoſtle did call that ſuche fornicacion as h<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ad not bene hard of / and therfore he did ſharpely rebuke yt and greuouſly correcte yt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lſo Theophilacte expoundinge the v. Chapiter prime Epiſtole ad Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inthios / doith ſuppoſe that the fath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of this Corintheane was a lyue / when that this yonge man maryed his mother in lawe. For Thephilacte doith cal t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hat mariage adultry / and alſo in a nother place expoundyng ſtil the ſame Chapiter / he callith t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>his Corinthians acte agayne adultry / And the abuſion that man doith with a woman that is n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ot maryed is not callid adultry / Wherfore by th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe yt ſemyth that thys yonge mans father was a
<pb facs="tcp:11164:16"/> lyue when that he maryed his Fathers wife</p>
               <p>¶ Radulphe of Laundun expoundinge the .vii chapiter of the ſecond Piſtill ad Corinthios doith ſay / this yongman toke awaye his fathers wyfe / and ſo he did his father iniury and wronge.</p>
               <p>¶ Iohn de ruppella expoundinge the reherſhid Chapiter ſaith the ſame.</p>
               <p>¶ Peter de Tarantaſe vppon the ſame Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter do likewiſe affirme and ſaye.</p>
               <p>¶ In the .xxij. leif of their boke thay ſaye that ſayncte Iohn Baptiſte did reproue herode the kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge by cauſe he had maried his brothers wyfe and he ſhewid the kinge that ſuche mariage was not leful nor that kinge Herode coulde not kepe his b<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rothers wyfe: this is trewth for Herode had ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried his Brothers wife / his brother beyng a lyue as ſhewith ſaynte Ierome in commentarijs ſuper Mattheum. Cap. xiiij. And ſo do Ioſoph the gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at ſtoriagraphe of the Iues libro .xviij. Antiquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atis Capite. ix. And alſo the ſame Ioſeph againe in the ſame boke. Cap. xi. ſaith that king Herodis brother was a lyue when that Herode maried his brothers wife. And lykewiſe doith ſaye the olde wryter and doctour Egeſipe Libro ſecundo Capite quinto of the deſtruccion of Ieruſalem.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:11164:16"/>
               <p>¶ Druthmar writinge vppon ſayncte Math<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ewe ſayth Herodes Brother Philipp was a lyue when that Herode toke awaye his brothers wife / and therfor ſayncte Iohn did rebuke kyng Herode</p>
               <p>¶ Hugh Cardinall writinge vppon Matthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we ſaith that Philip Herodes Brother was a ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue when that Herode toke awaye his wife and m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aried hyr / and therfore ſayncte Iohn did rebwke Kynge Herode.</p>
               <p>¶ Albart the great writer vppon ſayncte M<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arke ſayth that Iohn did rebwke King Herode be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cauſe he had maryed his Brothers wife his brot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>her beynge than a lyue.</p>
               <p>¶ Alſo the interlynyall gloyſe ſhewith vppon Matthew that Herodes Brother was a lyue w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hen Herod toke awaye his brothers wife / and ſo dothe manye diuerſe other doctours.</p>
               <p>¶ Sayncte Iohn therfore did iuſtly reproue k<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge herode for he did nowght to mary his broth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers wife hir huſband beynge a lyue / but now ſayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cte Iohn did not ſaye that a man might not leful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mary his brothers wife a widow lefte without yſſew / For ſayncte Iohn knew very well that ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che mariages were good and lefull and commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did in the lawe. So now ye may perceve that this ſaynge of ſayncte Iohn doithe nothinge fauoure
<pb facs="tcp:11164:17"/> thies decevers purpoſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow in the .xxvi. leife of their boke they bringe in the counſels of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtils that they kept in Iheruſalem where the Apoſtils decreyd that the gentils that were new come in to cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtis faithe ſhuld abſteyne and forbere fornicacion / and forbere to ete of any beſte / byrde / or foule that was ſuffocate or ſtranguled / and to forbere to ete any maner of fleſſhe that was offered to ydols / &amp; to forbere to ete blode as to forbere to ete puddyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es that be made of blode / and nowe thies deceuers affyrme that in / and vnder the name of fornicaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Apoſtils did forbide that a man ſhuld ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry his brothers wife a widow left with out yſſewe But this is very falſe / for fornicacion was alwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ys forbyden in euery law / But for a man to mary his brothers wife a widowe left withoute yſſewe / was neuer forbidden in the lawe of nature nor yn the olde lawe / nor in the newe / but as ye haue ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rde / ſuche mariage was in every lawe good and l<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>efull. Wherfore you maye ſee that it is falſe to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ye that the Apoſtils vnder the name of fornicaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on did forbid that a man ſhuld marey his Brothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rs wife a widowe left without yſſewe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Nd agayne theſe perſons can ſhew no doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our that ſo expoundith the decre of the apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtils. Here you maye ſee howe theſe decey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers
<pb facs="tcp:11164:17"/> do expound and apply ſcripture falſly for th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eyr falſe purpoſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Owe where as thies perſons in the .xxvij. leif of ther boke bryng in Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulyan the which they ſay doth affy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rme that this Leuiticall forbiddynge that a man ſhuld not mary his broth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers wife / was brought in / tawght / and ordyned ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially and by name of Chriſte hym ſelf / and his apoſtils / becauſe that all the hole churche and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mpany of Criſtes faithe ſhuld obſerue an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> kepe yt with deuocion and reuerence. This thies perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ns ſaye Tertulian writeth: but yet it helpith them no thing / for their falſe purpoſe: for after th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yr w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riting and allegyng of Tertulian / he ſaith that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Leuiticall forbidding that a man ſhulde not mary his brothers wife was brought in and tawght / and ordyned ſpecially and by name of Criſte hym ſelf / &amp; his apoſtils. &amp; I ſhew you that for a man to mary his broth<hi rend="sup">r</hi>s wyf a widow left without yſſew ys not forbidden by the leuitical law: and therfore this auctor helpeth thies perſones not a whit.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow where as thies perſones do bring in Tertuliane agayne in the .xxix. leif and in the .xxx. leif: that ſayth the com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dment that bounde the Iues to ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry theyr broth<hi rend="sup">r</hi>s wife widowe left without yſſew ys now ded and ceaſſed: &amp; the contrary of this law
<pb facs="tcp:11164:18"/> hath place: and he ſhewith why the commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ys nowe caeſſed / for the cauſes wherfore ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che mariage was commaunded in the olde lawe / be now taken awaye. And ther he ſhewith .iij. ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſes why almyghty God did commaund the Iues to mary their brothers wifes widowes left with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out yſſewe.</p>
               <p>¶ The firſt was becauſe almyghty God wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ld that the olde bliſſynge / Encreaſſe yow and m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ultiply / owght than to run forth and continew.</p>
               <p>¶ The ſeconde cauſe he ſaith was this: For aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muche as the childern were punyſhed for the fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hers fawtes than.</p>
               <p>¶ Thyrdly for bycauſe that the dry and baren perſons were had for defamyd perſons.</p>
               <p>¶ Here be now the cauſes that tertullian alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gethe why almyghty God did commaunde in the old lawe that euery man ſhuld mary his brothers wife a widowe left without yſſew. And for aſmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che as thies cauſes (after Tertulians mynd) be n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ow takyn awaye / therfore he ſaith that the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundment that bownd the Iues to mary theyr brothers wifes ys now ceaſſyd and ded / and the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trary of this taketh now place.</p>
               <p>¶ Firſt here I will anſwere to theſe reaſons: ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond
<pb facs="tcp:11164:18"/> I will ſhew yow how this commaundement that a man ſhulde always mary his brothers w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ife a widowe left without yſſew / ys now ceaſſyd &amp; deid: And thyrdly how this is falſe to ſaye that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> contrary of that commaundment haith now place And finally I will ſhew yow / for what reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble cauſes almyghty God did commaund the Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es to mary theyr brothers wifes widowes left w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ithout yſſewe.</p>
               <p>¶ Now I will turne to the reaſons of Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iane wher as he ſaith that the cauſe that almygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God did commaund his people the iues to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry theyr brothers wifis widows left without yſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ew / was for by cauſe as yet the olde bliſſing of god Encreaſſe yow and multiply / owght to run forthe and continew. This cauſe ys nothing worthe nor yet meyt to ſhewe why almyghty God ſhuld co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mmaund y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> brothers to mary theyr brothers wyfs widows &amp;c. For yf other men beſide the brothern had maryed the widows of the Iues that were le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ft without yſſew / the olde bliſſyng of God / Encr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe yow / and multyply / myght as wel haue run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nfurthe and contynewid as thowghe the Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers had maryed theyr Brothers widowes lefte without yſſew.</p>
               <p>¶ This no man can deny: therfore Tertulians reaſon yt but ſmall.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:11164:19"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>he ſecond cauſe that Tertuliane doth aſſigne why almyghty God did co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde the Iues to mary theyr bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wifes widows &amp;c. was this: for bicauſe than the children were pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yſhed for their fathers fawtes / and euery man no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we ys punyſhed for his owne ſyn / this is not trew For almyghty God ſaith by his Prophet Ezech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iel that the ſoon ſhall not be punyſhed for his fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hers fautes.<note place="margin">Ezech. xviij</note> Alſo yt were agaynſt reaſon that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myghty God ſhuld make a lawe to punyſhe the childe for the fathers fautis / when the childe is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent / and the father fautie / alſo yt were more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt reaſon to punyſhe the childe for the fautes of his owne father natural / and for the fautes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of his father that is his father but by the law: wherfore this can be no reſonable cauſe why alm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yghty God did commaund the Iues to mary the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yr brothers wifes widows left without yſſew.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He thirde cauſe that Tertulian doith aſſigne why almyghty God did com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund the Iues to mary their brothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s wifis widows left with out yſſewe was this: bycauſe that the barren and dry perſons were hade for defamyd perſons: therfore an ordin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce was made that they ſhuld haue yſſew by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of their kyn as you wold ſaye by a proctour / This cauſe lykewyſe is nothinge worthe / for the dry and barren perſons myght as well haue had
<pb facs="tcp:11164:19"/> yſſewe / yf other perſons / beſides their brothern a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nd kinſfolke / had maryed their wifes widows &amp;c. as though their brothern had maryed theyr wido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ws / this is euydent / Wherfore thies ſaynges of Tertulyan do not ſeme to be cauſes why that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myghty God dyd commaund the Iues to marye their brothers wifes widowes left without yſſew</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Owe to the ſeconde poynte that I ſayd I wold ſhewe you that this commaundm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent that bounde the Iues to mary alw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ays theyr brothers wyfes widowes lefte without yſſewe / is now ceaſſed and ded: that is to ſaye / th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at no man now / Iue nor Gentile / nor Chriſten-man is bounde to mary his brothers wife a wido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we left with out yſſew vnder a payne. For this co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mmaundment was in the olde lawe a Iudiciall: and all thoſe commaundements be ded and ceaſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Nowe as touchinge the bonde and payne / t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>his is trewe: But yet yt folowith not of this th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at now it is agaynſt the lawe of God and agay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nſt the law of nature for a man to mary his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wife a widow left without yſſew / and that the Pope haith no power to diſpence vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>riage: &amp; ſo it is falſe / which is the thyrde poynte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> I ſayd I wold ſhew you / to ſaye that this iudici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al commaundme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / that bound men to mary theyr brothers wifis widows &amp;c. ys ceaſſed and ded aft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er this facio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: &amp; thꝰ y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to haue place as ye m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ay ſe by exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple. If a king in his realme wold make
<pb facs="tcp:11164:20"/> this lawe that who ſo euer put out a mans eye ſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ulde leſe his owne eye for it / who than coulde ſay that this lawe were now agaynſt the lawe of god and agaynſt the lawe of nature? trewly no man And yet this was a Iudicial commaundme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and lawe with the Iues the whiche is now ceaſſid and ded: that ys to ſaye / it byndith no more now by th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at lawe. And yet the ſame may agayne be a newe conſtitucion. ye and likewiſe this commaundment myght haue be made agayne by the churche / that a man in certayne cauſes ſhuld haue bene bownd to haue maryed his brothers wife a widow left w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ithout yſſew. Wherfore yow maye ſee / that it is f<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alſe to ſaye that this commaundment that boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de men to mary their brothers wifs widows &amp;c. ys now ceaſſid and ded / and the contrary nowe to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue place is falſe to: that is to ſaye / that it is nowe ageynſt the lawe of God and lawe of nature / for a man to mary his Brothers wife a widowe &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lſo that this is falſe / yt is euident bi the opynion that Tertulyane helde and did conclude vppon this ſayng: for Tertuliane had this opynion / t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hat it was vnlawfull for any wom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an to mary agayne after the deth of hyr huſband / Thus he makith his reaſon / the lawe is ceaſſid wherby a man ſhuld be bound to mary his Broth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers wife / wherfor if a womans huſband be ded ſhe maye not mary her huſbandes Brother / for that
<pb facs="tcp:11164:20"/> is now forbidden: and ſhe may not mary eny heyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hen man: for that is lykewiſe forbidden to euery criſten woman: and all Chriſten people be broth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ern in God ergo &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>ll this ſaynge is Tertulians / and of this ſaynge it folowith that a wom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an after the deth of hir huſband m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ay mary no more. For firſt Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iane faith that a woman after the d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth / of hir huſband may not mary hir huſbandes brother / for that / he ſaith is now forbiden / and all Criſtenmen be brothern in Chriſte: and ſo than by that meane they be brothern to hir huſband t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hat is dede: and than ſhe may not mary any of th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>em / nor agayne / ſhe may mary no heythen man / f<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or that Tertuliane ſaith is forbidden alſo: Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he concludethe that no Criſten woman maye mary after the deth of hyr huſband: the whiche I ſaye is falſe / and ageinſt the holy Apoſtil ſaynge where as he writeth / that yf a womans huſbande doo dy / let hyr mary / ſayth he / where ſhe will / ſo that ſhe mary a Criſten man.<note place="margin">i. cor vij</note> And Tertuliane in his ſaynge / and boke that he writ it he yt in / ys conuicte and condemnid for hereſy. And thus I ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ye therfore it is falſe / and heretical to ſaye / and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyrme / that this commaundment that bounde the Iues to mary theyr brothers wifis widows &amp;c. ys now ded and ceaſſid and the contrary hathe place: that is to ſaye / that yt is now forbidden by the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we
<pb facs="tcp:11164:21"/> of God and by the cawe of nature that a man ſhuld mary his brothers wife a widow left with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out yſſew. And the Pope hath no power to diſpen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce vppon ſuche mariage.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lſo by brynging in that heretike Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuliane on this wife and in the boke th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at ys condemned for hereſy / you may perceue with what ſpirit and conſciens thies perſons haue writen and made theyr boke / Here thei leve owt the bokes name / w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>her they allege Tertulian: and they ſaye on this wiſe in the .xxviij. leif of their boke: and the ſame Tertuliane writith in an other place / and ſo they leve owt the name of the boke: whiche in dede is c<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allid monogamia the whiche boke is condemnid. Alſo in theyr ynglyſſhe boke thei leue out parte of Tertulians ſayng and argument / wher he wold haue concluded to haue condempned the ſecond m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages. By this you euidently perceue that thies perſons opinion &amp; ſayng / where they affirme that it is againſt the lawe of God and ageynſt the law of nature / for a man to mary his brothers wife a widow left without yſſewe ys euidently falſe: ye and ſuſpecte hereticall / ſeynge that they goo about to proue their reherſed opynion and ſaynge / by ter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tulian wher he is condemned for an heretike. Now to the fowrth I wil ſhew ye / for what reſonable c<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>auſes it was comaundid in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> olde law y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euery man ſhuld mary his brothers wife / a widow left &amp;ce.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:11164:21"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>he firſt was that the land is of the iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es the which ſhuld goo and continew by inheritaunce / ſhuld not goo owte of the blode / and name and houſe th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at it cam of / and therfore it was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundid to the Iues that they myght not ſel the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ir inheritaunce:<note place="margin">leuiti. xxv.</note> a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d than it was commaundid and ordyned that if a man died without yſſew that his brother (if he had any / <note place="margin">Deute. xxv</note> or els his next kinneſman) ſhulde mary his wife / and the firſt childe that th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is ſeconde brother hade by his brothers wife / ſhuld be namyd the firſt brothers childe and enioy his l<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ande and ſo kepe vp the ded mans houſe and name Wherfore holy Criſoſtome ſaithe that almyghty God in commaunding theiues to mary their bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wifes widows left without yſſewe / <note place="margin">Super mat. ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>melia. xlix.</note> did exc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ogite and made a meane to counfort ſuche perſons as ſhuld chaunce to dye without yſſew. This ys holy Criſoſtomes mynde / ſo by this commaund<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and lawe if he chaunced to dye without yſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we he was in a ſuerty that the next of his blode ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>huld enioy and inheret his landes / and vpholde h<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is houſe and name / the which was alwais to him y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſo died a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte. For euery man naturalli had le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> one of his own blode ſhuld enioy &amp; haue his landes than a ſtraunger not of his kyn / alſo euery man wold gladly haue his name &amp; houſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he cam of / to remayn &amp; continew: alſo beſide this conforte that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> man had / this lawe was a mene to confort y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> widow who is huſband dyed without yſſew / for
<pb facs="tcp:11164:22"/> thowgh ſhe lefte hyr huſband / yet ſhe was ſuer to be maryed agayne to one of his next kyn / whiche was no ſmall counforte to hyr / to be in a ſuerte to mary one that ſhe louyd for hyr huſbandes ſake: and alſo to mary one that louid hyr for hyr huſb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andis ſake: Alſo this maner of mariage was a m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eane to cauſe hyr huſbandes kynred to bere and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we loue and fauour ſtyll vnto the woman that h<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ad buryed hyr firſt huſband: for by cauſe ſhe mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yed agayne hyr huſbandis kynſman for whos ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke this kindred had loued hir huſband before: the whiche loue wold ſone haue wexid colde and gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wn ſklender toward the wedow / if ſhe had maryd out of hir huſbandis kyndred / as we may ſee / dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by experyence. And finally / this maner of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iage was a ſpeciall meane to kepe and continew y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loue and kyndenes that was betwene the woma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ns kynred and the kynred of hyr firſt huſband: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche loue / and kyndenes wold haue mynyſhed and haue decayd / if the wife had maryed out of hir huſbandis kindred / wherfore ſo to marye was a ſpeciall meane to kepe loue and kyndenes betwene kindredis. And yf ſum of thies cauſes had ſtrength now in this Realme by an ordinaunce decreyd / th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ey wold not be iuged but good and reſonable / As this that no man ſhuld ſell his inheritaunce / nor agayne that many inheritaunces ſhuld neuer co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me to one mans hande / this were parauenture a good and a reſonable law. So thus yowe maye ſee that thies be reſonable and honeſte cauſes / and po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liticall
<pb facs="tcp:11164:22"/> meanis / and very mete for that tyme for t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>he comen welth of the Iues: and therfore almyg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gty God made this lawe that euery one of the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues ſhulde always mary their brothers wifes w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>idows left without yſſewe: And commaunded the Iues to kepe it / Wherfor you may euidently perc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eue that it can not be againſte the lawe of nature and reaſon for a man to mary his brothers wife a widow &amp;c. And alſo it is hy blaſphemy to almyg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hty God to ſaye that he with his infinite ſapience and wiſdom did make a lawe againſte reaſon and commaunde it to be kepte vppon a great payne. But now where as thies perſons ſaye that this lawe that commaundid ſuche mariage / ys now d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and hath no ſtrengthe: ſewerly that is trew for men (as I ſhewed ye before) but yet ſtandeth it in theyr lyberty to mary or not marye their brothers wifes widows &amp;ceter. and ſo it doith not follow t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hat it is now ageynſte the law of God and agey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nſte the lawe of nature for a man to mary his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wife a widow left without yſſew: and that the pope can not diſpence vppon ſuche mariage.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the .xxx. leif of their boke they b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nge in Gregory anſweryng to a que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion that ſaynte Auguſtyne had m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouid concerning mariage with in deg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reys of affinyte / ſaynge on this wiſe. There is a certayn erthly and a worldly lawe w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ith in the dominacion of Rome / that the ſone and
<pb facs="tcp:11164:23"/> the doughter of brother and ſiſter or of .ij. brothers germayne / or of .ij. ſiſters / may mary togither: but we haue lernid by experience that ther coulde ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer yſſew cum of ſuche mariage. To this it maye be thꝰ anſweryd: that nowe at this preſent time t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>her ys comen of ſuche mariage noble and great yſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſew: as the Emperours children: for the Empero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wr and his wife that now ys / came of .ij. ſiſters ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rmane / for the Emperours mother and his wifes mother where both ſiſters and doughters to Don Ferdinando that was kyng of ſpayne. Alſo we m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ay ſe great and noble yſſewe that is come of a man that maryd .ij. ſiſters germane the whiche maria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge ys hyer in the degreys of affinite than is the c<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hildren of the brother and ſiſter germane in conſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nguinite. As the kyng of Portingall that now is / and his brothern and the Emperours wife and h<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yr ſiſters the whiche cam of the Kynge of Portin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaill / this mans father that maryd two ſiſters g<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ermane that were both doughters to Don Ferdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nando Kynge of ſpayne. And this ſayd Kynge of Portingaill had by bothe thies ſiſters yſſewe / ye and yet after the deth of thies two ſiſters / his wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fes / he mariyd the thyrde ſiſters doughter the w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hiche lady is now the frenche Kynges wife: and by this lady alſo the ſayd Kynge of Portynga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ill hade yſſewe whiche ys yet a lyue: Wherfo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re we maye ſee that of ſuche mariage cumythe yſſewe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:11164:23"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the .xxxj. leif of their boke thies pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons do aduertyſe the reder to marke iij. or .iiij. thinges of Gregores ſayng. Firſt that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leuitical lawes wher it is forbidden that a man ſhuld mary his brothers wife with the other / be the very lawes of allmyghty God / And now the ſame lawes be of the ſame ſtrength that it is not lefull to contracte matrymoney contrary to that which is forbid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en in the ſame. This ſaynge helpith no thinge to th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ies deceyuers pupoſe: for it is not forbidden in the Leuiticall lawe that a man maye not mary his b<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rothers wyfe a wydowe &amp; cetera. As I haue often ſayd before. Moreouer thies perſons ſaye that ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynte Gregory writeth that the occaſion of ſaynte Iohns martyrdome was this / by cauſe he wolde mayntayne and vpholde the trewth of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me lawes agaynſte Herode the kynge / whiche had maryed hys Brothers wife. This ſaynge lyk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ewyſe makith no thinge for thies perſons purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe. Firſt for by cauſe that for a man to mary h<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ys Brothers wyfe a widowe lefte withowte yſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ewe / it is not agaynſte the trwthe and aucto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of the Leuiticall lawe: for there ys no ſuche Mariage forbidden there / nor ſaynte Iohn did not ſuffer martyrdome for reprouynge of Kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge Herode / for mariynge hys Brothers wife a widowe left withowte yſſewe: for he did not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue Kynge Herode for ſuche Mariage. But he reprouyd Kynge Herode by cawſe he had
<pb facs="tcp:11164:24"/> mareyd his brothers wife / hir huſband his broth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er than beynge a lyue: and ſo in that kyng Herode did agaynſte the lawe of nature / and agaynſt the leuiticall law / and if ſaynte Iohn did vpholde the trwth and the auctorite of the Leuitical lawe: we muſt ſuppoſe that lykewiſe he wold vpholde the trouth of the Deuteronomicall commaundement that bound the Iues to mary their brothers wifes widows left without yſſew / and than it is manif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſte that ſaynte Iohn ſpekith no thinge that can make for thies menys falſe purpoſe / In the ſame leif thies perſons do affirme that Gregory doith write that mariages whiche certayne ynglyſſhe men had contracte with their brothers wifes / and that euen before they had taken them: ſaith vpon them to be ſo vnleful and not to be ſpoken / that th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ey coulde notwithout dedly ſyn render the dewty of mariage one to a nother / nor yet abide ſtil in the ſame mariage. Here thies perſons ſay falſly vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon Gregory and agaynſte his wordes and agay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nſt his minde. For Gregory did admitte thoſe yn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glyſhmen that had maryed their brothers wifes to be Criſten / and to retayne and kepe ſtill theyr wifes and alſo to cum into the churche and receyue the bleſſed Sacrament of the Auter / the whiche Gregory wolde in no cauſe haue ſufferd / yf he had Iuged ſuche mariage to haue ben agaynſt the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we of God and againſt the law of nature / nor yet Gregory wolde haue ſufferd thies yngliſhmen to haue continewed ſtill with their wifes / yf it had
<pb facs="tcp:11164:24"/> bene dedly ſyn to them to haue continewed withe their wifes: And therfore ye may ſee that thies p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erſons ſpeke directly agaynſte Gregoris mynde: alſo ye ſhal ſe that they ſpeke agaynſte Gregoris wordis if ye wil loke vpon Gregory / but Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry did exhorte and teche the yngliſhemen that w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ere new comen to the faith / that they ſhuld no m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ore mary as they had done before / and made them lawes of matrimoney that they ſhuld not marye theyr kynſwomen in the firſt degre of affinite or conſanguinite nor in the ſecond / nor in the thyrde / nor in the fowerthe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat they write alſo in the .xxxij. leif of their boke: that Gregory ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we that mariage betwene the bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and the brothers wife a wido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we &amp;c. of this mariage they ſpeke to be playnly vngodly and iuged it ab<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hominable before God and man and alſo agayne the nature of man / and as nyghe as can be vnto the nature a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d lyfe of beſtis. This thies perſons ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aye Gregory ſawe and did iuge ſuche matrimony o to be. In the whiche ſaynge they affirme that ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aynte Gregory doith blaſpheme almyghty God: and alſo his holy lawe: for if Gregory ſawe and iuged mariage betwene the brother and the broth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers wife / to be abhominable and odious to God &amp; man / and alſo to be againſt the nature of man / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d as nyghe as can be vnto the nature and lyfe of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtis
<pb facs="tcp:11164:25"/>
/ than muſt it nedes folowe that ſaynte Greg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ory ſawe that almyghty god in commandinge ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che mariage did commaunde that thing that was abhominable and odyous to God and man / and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lſo that thinge that is ageynſte the nature of man and that thing that is as nyghe as can be to the n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ature and lyfe of beſtis: for as I haue ſhewed yow almyghty God did commaunde ſuche mariage / &amp; alſo by this their ſayng of ſaynte Gregory / yt do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ith folowe that he ſawe as myche abhominacyon in the lawe of God whiche commaundid the bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to mary the brothers wife a widow left wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hout yſſewe. And if it were ſo / than ſayncte Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory dyd blaſpheme godys lawe. Here ye maye ſee what thies perſons ſaye by ſaynte Gregory / alſo in the later ende of the ſame leif thies perſons ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ye that ſaynte Gregory ſawe how greuous pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yſhment is abydinge them whiche haue defylyd them ſelf with this fowl ſyn. That they vnderſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ande in the reherſed mariage: therfore he iugede t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hat nother peace / nor faith and Criſtendome / nor any other thinge in this worlde beſide forth / is of ſuche vertue and goodnes that is able to recomp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and waye owt the maliciouſnes of this dede: and ſo forthe / withe diuerſe grete and ſharpe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des as yow maye ſee in their boke.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow by this ſayng thies perſons do grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tly blaſpheme ſaynte Gregory and do ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ye that he blaſphemithe almyghty God / 
<pb facs="tcp:11164:25"/> for yf ſaynte Gregory ſhuld thus iuge by maria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge betwene the brother and the brothers wife a widowe &amp;c. Than ſaynte Gregory ſhuld iuge th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at almyghty God in commaundinge ſuche maria<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge / commaunded that thing that is ſo abhomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and ſo euill / that ther is no thing in this worl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de of ſuche vertu and goodnes that is able to reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mpence and waye owt the maliciouſnes of this d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ede / Who euer harde any man ſaye that almygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God wolde commaunde ſo abominable a thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge as theſe perſons ſaye Gregory iugithe maria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge betwene the brother and the brothers wife wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owe &amp;c. to be? And ſuche mariage commaundid al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mighty God:<note place="margin">Ancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me</note> wherfore this in no wiſe may be G<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regoris iugement nor mynd: for Anceſme (as thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es deceyuers do allege) ſaith in a Piſtell / that for certain honeſte cauſes there were holy men bothe before the law / &amp; in the law / that did mary in the firſt and ſeconde degre of conſanguynite / as Abr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aam Iſaac &amp; Iacob:<note place="margin">Ioſ. xv ther m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ay be h<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oneſt c<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>auſes why a man m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ay ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry his ſiſter. in libro. de Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riarcha abraam</note> In the lawe Caleb y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> maryd his brothers doughter / than if ther may be honeſt cauſes why a man may mary his ſiſter / ther may be honeſt cauſes why a man maye marye his Br<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>others wyfe a widow &amp; cetera. And than it folow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ithe that by ſum honeſt cauſe ther maye be a reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mpence for any offence in ſuche mariage.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lſo ſaynte Ambroſe doith excuſe the dough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Lothe / ſaynge that the good zele th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at they had for to conſerue mankynde / the whiche
<pb facs="tcp:11164:26"/> they thowght ſhulde haue periſhed) did reward t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hem ſo vniuerſally / that it coueryd their inhone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte priuate acte / and than it folowith that yf their good zele that they had did excuſe their particula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re faute / ther may be ſum thinge in this worlde of ſuche vertue and goodnes that it is able to recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe and waye owt the maliciouſnes of matrim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oney betwene the brother and the brothers wife a widow &amp;c. For in this or ſuche mariage is none of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence agaynſt the lawe of God nor againſt the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we of nature / as ye haue hard before. Wherfore it ſemith by this that ſaynte Gregoris mynde was neuer to iuge ſuche mariage to be ſo euyl as thies perſons wold haue hym to do.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Or Gregoris wordis do not ſo ſownde nor ſignifie / nor Gregory doith not ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aye that it is againſt the law of God and againſt the lawe of nature for a man to mary his brothers wife a wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owe &amp;c. And that the Pope haith no power to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence vpon ſuche mariage / and ſo al that thies p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erſons bringe in of Gregory do nothinge helpe th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eyr malicyouſe purpoſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the .xxxiij. leyf of theyr boke they bringe in Pope zachary / the which an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerd the biſhop Theodore to his que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion whether that a mans natural ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one maye marye with his fathers god
<pb facs="tcp:11164:26"/> doughter? and the Pope anſwerid on this wiſe / we be / ſaith he / by the lawe of God comaundid to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtayne from owr owne kyndred Carnal / mychm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ore it is conuenient that we ſhuld with all ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th be ware of hyr that ys owr fathers doughter ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piritual / Wher vppon thies perſones wolde conc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lude that it is againſt the lawe of God and aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynſte the lawe of nature for a man to mary his b<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rothers wife a widowe left without yſſew: and th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at the Pope hath no power to diſpence vppon ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>he mariage / But this ſaynge of Pope zachary di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly agaynſt their concluſion. For of his ſaynge it folowith / that the Pope maye diſpence and lice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nce the brother to mary the ſiſter / and than it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owith that the Pope may licence a man to marye his brothers wife a widowe left without yſſewe. for it is no more forbidden for a man to marye his brothers wife a widowe &amp;cete. than it is for a man to mary his ſiſter / but the pope hath power by th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is zacharias ſaynge / to licens a man to marye hys ſiſter. This you ſhal ſee prouyd. The Pope hath power to licence a man to mary his fathers godo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ughter / for that affinite doith not let mariage by no lawe / but onely by the lawe of the churche / as of it ſelf it is euident / and the Pope maye diſpence againſt the puer prohibicion of the churche: Wh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfore the Pope may licence a man to mary his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers goddoughter / and now Pope zachary ſaithe that it is more forbidden that a man ſhuld mary his fathers goddoughter than his fathers dough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:11164:27"/>
/ and yet vppon ſuche mariage the Pope hathe power to diſpence: Wherfore than he haith power to diſpence that the brother may mary the ſiſter / for yf the Pope maye diſpence in the thing that is more prohibit / he may diſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in that thing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe prohibite / and than further / if the Pope may di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpence vppon mariage betwene the brother and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſiſter / he hath than power to diſpence vpon maria<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge betwene the brother and the brothers wife a w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>idowe &amp;c. This you ſe doith followe of this Pope zachary his ſayng / the whiche makith for the tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wth / and againſt thies deceyuers falſe concluſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the ſame leif thies perſons do bry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nge in the gloſe that doith goo vppon the wordes of Pope zachary / the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che gloſe doith make argumentis th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at the Pope can not diſpence thoughe he wold / in the ſeconde degre of conſanguinite nor yet in the ſecond degre of the firſt maner of affini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te / for the ſecond degre of conſanguinite and of th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is affinite hath / his begynninge of the lawe of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture / and agayne bycauſe of the ſame degre it is forbidden expreſly in the olde teſtament of God. Here thies perſons ſhewe that the gloſer maki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th Argumentis / and ſaye that the Pope cannot (thoughe he wolde) diſpence in the ſeconde degre of conſanguinite nor in the ſeconde degre of the firſte maner of affinite &amp;c. But they will not ſhew yow how the ſame gloſer doith alſo make arguments
<pb facs="tcp:11164:27"/> to ſhewe that the Pope may diſpence in theyſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greys of conſanguynite and of affinite / and yet y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame gloſer makith argumentis for bothe partes and finally he determineth nother this / that the p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ope may diſpence / nor yet this / that the Pope can not diſpence / but this theſe deceyuers wil not reh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erſe in their boke / and ſo nowe ye maye ſee that the gloſer whiche they do allege doith nothynge for their purpoſe / And alſo if the gloſe had ſayd that the Pope coulde not haue diſpencyd in the reherſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d degreys of conſanguinite and of affinite / he h<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ad ſpoken directly agaynſte the texte: for the tex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te ſayth that affinite ſpirituall in the firſte degre ys more forbidden (in the whiche the Pope may di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpence) than ys conſanguynite Carnall in the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me degre / as you haue hard before / and thus thies perſons wold haue the gloſſe to deſtroye the texte whiche can not be.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irthermore they bringe in Pope Inn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ocent the thyrde to whom ſent the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>diacon of biturs to know wheth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er that wife that was departed from hir huſband without iugement of the churche / by cauſe hir huſband and ſhe were in ſo n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yghe degre of kyndred that the ſea Apoſtolyk co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ulde not / nor yet was wonte to diſpence with / ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght to be reſtored agayne to hyr huſbande? marke wel this queſtyon and caſe that this archediacon
<pb facs="tcp:11164:28"/> aſked of the Pope: and than yowe ſhall and maye perceue better the Popis anſwere that he made to the queſtion and caſe / The Pope anſwerithe and ſayth this woman whiche doith knowe the kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red betwene hir huſband and hir ſpecially in thies degres whiche be forbidden by the law of God can not haue to do Carnally withe this hir huſband without dedly ſyn / and ſo finally the Pope ſaith t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hat the woman ſhal not be reſtored agayne to hyr huſband. Here the Pope anſwerith verey wel / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d no thinge for thies mens purpoſe. For as the caſe was put furth in general / ſo that caſe purpoſed / the Pope anſwereth in generall / that is to ſaye t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hat yf a woman whiche was departed frome hyr huſband without iugement of the churche becauſe hir huſband / and ſhe were in ſo nyghe degre of ky<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nred / that he ſea Apoſtolik coulde not / nor yet w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as not wont / to diſpence with yt: Than ſaith the Pope if the woman knewe this / and ſo vppon th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is is departyd from hir huſband ſhe may not be r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtored to hyr huſband agayne / nor ly withe hym without dedly ſyn. For how coulde ſhe be reſtored to hyr huſband agayne or company with hym w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ithout dedly ſyn? When that ſhe knew hyr huſba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nd ſo nere to hyr of kyn that in kepinge hym com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pany / and to be reſtored to hym / ſhe ſhuld do aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynſt the law of God / and that the Pope could not diſpence with hyr that ſhe myght turn agayne to hir huſband / nor he was not wonte to diſpence in ſuche a caſe: all this is trwthe / but all this is in g<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eneral:
<pb facs="tcp:11164:28"/> for it is not ſhewid in what degre of kynr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the woman could not be reſtored agayne to hyr huſbande / nor in what degre the Pope could not / nor was not wont to licence a woman that was departed from hyr huſband to be reſtored agayne. And ſo all this ſaynge of Pope Innocent makith no thinge for thies mens purpoſe. For the caſe that they ſpeke of / ys particuler and ſpeciall that ys it againſte the lawe of God and agaynſte the lawe of nature for a man to mary his Brothers wife a widowe &amp;ce. And that the Pope hath no power to diſpencr vppon ſuche mariage. This Pope innoc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent doith not ſaye / nor vppon all his ſayng / this no man can conclude / But this Pope innocent ys directly againſt this falſe opinion / as it is manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte in the chapiter. Deus qui Eccleſiam. Where yt appereth that he ſufferd the Iues whiche turned to Criſte and receyued Baptiſm to continwe ſtill with their Brothers wifes that they had maryed before. But the heythens that turnyd and receyu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed baptiſm / the ſayd Pope wold not ſuffer them to haue mo wifes then one: which befor had maryed them to mo. And thus by this may ye ſe that Pope innocent ys againſt thies deceuers falſe opinion / &amp; likwiſe he is agaynſt them in the chap. Gaudemꝰ.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the .xxxvi. leif they ſaye. Now beſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de all this we ſhall proue the ſame by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> auctorite of holy counſels. This they mean that they will proue by the auct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orite
<pb facs="tcp:11164:29"/> of holy councels that it is againſte the lawe of God and againſte the lawe of nature for a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to mary his brothers wife / a widowe left without yſſew &amp;c. To all the councells that theſe perſons do bringe in / yt may be brefely anſwered / that the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re is none of them that ſaye yt is agaynſt the law of God / and againſte the lawe of nature / for a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to mary his brothers wife a widowe lefte without yſſew / nor yet this. That the Pope hath no pow<hi rend="sup">r</hi> to diſpence vppon ſuche mariages.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Oreouer ye muſt note that the prohibi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cions that the counſels haue decreyd to let mariage in degreys of affinite / were not made for bycauſe ſuche affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite did ſet mariage by the law of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture as it is manifeſt / in the thyrde and fowerthe degre of affinite: no more ys the firſt nor the ſecond degre in the right lyne in the ſecond lyne after the mynde of thies perſons great doctour / Peter de Pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lude: for he ſaith vppon the .xviij. Chapiter of the Leuiticall boke that the Pope maye diſpence in all the degreys of affinite there conteyned.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow where as there be diuerſe counſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ls and many decreys and ſaynges of fathers that do forbide that a man ſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al not mary his ſiſter / his brothers w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ife / his nece / nor his coſin germane: of ſych counſells decreys and ſaynges / a man maye
<pb facs="tcp:11164:29"/> gather that in the begynninge of Criſtes churche the people did vſe comenly to mary their ſiſters / their brothers wifes / their nere kynſwomen: and ſuche as were nye to them in affinite / for els ſew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erly the councels and fathers wolde not haue ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ſo often of ſuche mariages as they did: for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience doith teche vs that counſels parliament<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is / and ſinodes do not often tymes make many de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creys agaynſte thos thinges that be not in vſe / but where therbe many decreys and lawes made agaynſte a thinge: the ſame decreys and lawes do euidently ſhew that the thinge that they ſpeke ſo muche agaynſt was greatly in vſe. Wherfore ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge that therbe diuerſe counſels and many decr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eys and ſaynges that do now forbide that the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhal not mary in the firſt degre of affinite / in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aſcendent lyne / nor in the ſide lyne / nor yete in the ſecond nor in the thirde degre of affinite: it ys euy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent that the people did vſe to mary in thies deg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reys before / and at the beginninge of the churche and than the peple lyued more iuſtly and godlyer than they doo now: Wherfore it folowith that for a man to mary his Brothers wife a widowe lefte withe owte &amp;cete. or in the ſecond degre of affini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te / can not be agaynſte the lawe of God / nor aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynſte the lawe of nature. For yf ſuche mariage h<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ad ben ſo euyll / the people that lyued ſo iuſtly and ſo holely before the prohibicions of ſuche Maria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge were made / and at the begynnynge of the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che / wolde neuer haue vſide ſuche Mariage.
<pb facs="tcp:11164:30"/> So now by this reaſon yowe maye ſee that the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unſaills and decreys that do forbid nowe ſuche m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ariage make agaynſte theſe Peſtilent perſons fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lſe opinyone.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Rewly the cauſe why thies Fathers and counſailles did orden and decre / that the people ſhuld no more marye with their kynred and affinite in the firſt / ſecond / and thirde degre / was t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>his. For aſmyche as thoſe holy Fathers and prel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ats did ſe and manifeſtly perceue that the charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble loue and kyndenes that was wont to be amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nge Criſten people did ſore mynyſhe and decay. Wherfore thies Fathers and Prelats ordenyd a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d decreyd that the Pope ſhuld mary all owt of their kinred and affynite / to knyte in loue ſuche people to gither by mariage that were not knyte to gith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in love by kynred and affinite. We ſe by comyn experyence that by mariage the kyndred of bothe the perſons that be maryd do loue togither: Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rfore the holy Fathers and conſailles did lymit o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wte certayn degreys of affinite and kindred in the whiche they ſuppoſid that loue wolde contynewe without the helpe of mariage / and ſo they did for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide and commaunde no man to mary in non of th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ies degres of affinite and kyndred without the P<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>opes licence. But that the people ſhuld mary owt of thies degres of kynred a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d affinite. This did th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ies Fathers and councels orden and commaund to
<pb facs="tcp:11164:30"/> the entent to ſpreyd abrode and ſowe loue and cha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rite by mariage amonge the people that were not ioynid togither in kynred and affinite. Here ye ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue hard the cauſes why the counſels and decreys did forbid mariage in the firſt / the ſeconde / and the thyrde / and fowerth degre of affinite and kyndred wherby ye may ſee that for a man to mary his br<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>others wife a widow &amp;ce. or his nece or coſyn ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane / ys not againſt the lawe of God / nor agay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nſt the lawe of nature: but againſte the lawe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> churche: with the whiche the Pope maye diſpence</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the .xxxvij. leif of their boke / thyes perſones bryng in the counſaile of N<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecene and the ſynode of Gregore the yongar: where it was decreyd accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge to the wordes of God: that a wo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>man whiche had ben maryed to .ij. Brothern ſhul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de be put bake frome communyon / and from the re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceyuinge of the ſacrement vntyl ſhe died / and a m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an that had maryed his brothers wife / ſhuld be an Anatheme / In the whiche ſynode / al to gither an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweryd / Anatheme be he / that is as myche to ſaye (as thies peſtilent perſones do expounde it) as da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mnacion to euerlaſtynge dethe / To this ſayng of the counſel and ſynode / I anſwere: that theyr ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nge and excommunycacion ys vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to be ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>plyed vnto ſuche perſons as do mary them ſelues in ſuche degreys of affinite without licence of the Pope. As that woman that doith mary hyr ſelf
<pb facs="tcp:11164:31"/> after the deth of hir huſband to hir huſbandes br<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other: and ſo in lyke wiſe / that man which marye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th his brothers wife a widowe &amp;cet. For they th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at preſume to mary on the reherſed maner / owght to be punyſhed as it is a fore ſpoken of: except that they be penitent and ſory for that they haue done / ye and leaue and forſake / the men their wifes / and the women their huſbandis: without the Pope ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cence them to mary the ſaide men and women th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at thei hade taken before / But yet the counſel and ſynode did not decre to punyſhe that woman / whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che after the deth of hir huſband / maried hir huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandis brother: nor yet the man whiche maryd his Brothers wife a widow &amp;c. for by cauſe they mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yed agaynſte the lawe of God / and agaynſte the lawe of nature / as it is manifeſt. For ther is noth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er the counſell / nor the ſynode that doith decre and ſaye that ſuche mariage is againſt the law of god and agaynſte the lawe of nature. But the counſel and ſynode did orden and decre the punyſhements before reherſed for ſuche perſons as did preſume to mary / as the woman with hir huſbandis brother / or the man with the Brothers widow againſt the prohibicion and decre of the churche / And ſo nowe this counſel and ſinode do not helpe thies vngrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ious perſones falſe opinion / But yet if theſe decey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers will ſaye that the ſinode and counſell / or any other decre or counſell doith forbid that a man ſhal not mary his brothers wife a widow &amp;c. for by ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſe that ſuche mariage is againſt the law of God
<pb facs="tcp:11164:31"/> and againſt the lawe of nature: when that they ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hew me this of any decre or counſell: I ſhalbe redy to make anſwere to it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the .xxxij. leif of their boke / they ſay on this wiſe laſt of all / and for a concluſion. That y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſentence of Wiklif wherin he did holde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the prohibicions of matrimoney writen in the Leuitic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al / be onely iudicial preceptis of Moyſes / &amp; therf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ore the cauſes of diuorce brought in by the meane of kinred &amp; of affinite to be brought in without g<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>round &amp; fundacion / &amp; onely by the ordinance of m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an / was condempnyd as contrary to all vertu a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d goodnes / &amp; as heretical / &amp; expreſly agaynſte holy ſcripture / in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great conuocation y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was firſt at Lon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>don / &amp; after at Oxforde: &amp; laſt of al in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> counſel of Conſtancy. Here theſe perſons ſaye falſly / &amp; they lye on Wicleffe: for Wik lef did neu<hi rend="sup">r</hi> ſay y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibicions of matrimoney writen in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leuiticall law be but only iudicials: nor y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uocation / nor yet the counſel doith not condempne Wiklyf in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> point: &amp; yet if he had ſayd / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al thies prohibicions of matri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>money had bene but onely Iudicials / &amp; the conuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacion and counſel to haue condempnyd hym for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame ſaynge / and to haue iuged all thies prohibici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to be moralles: yet al thies wold no thing ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue holpen thies deceuers fals opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: For as mych as in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leuitical prohibicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ys not forbid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> (as I of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten tymes ſayd) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal not mary his broth<hi rend="sup">r</hi>s
<pb facs="tcp:11164:32"/> wife a widowe lefte withoute yſſewe / and thus ye maye ſee that all that they bringe in / for them can do them no ſeruice.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the ſame leif of their boke / they ſay there be decres of other counſails and anſwers in writing of other of the po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pes whiche do ſubſcribe &amp; agree to th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ies forſayd determinacions / and a no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne after this / it folowithe in theyr boke. But we truſte ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>till a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d indifferent reder / that thies forſaid reherſyd thinges ſhal fully content the / for thow ſeyſt here firſt of all in maner an hole comen aſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nt and agrement of the holy churche / and firther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more thow ſeiſt the Popes them ſelues do gyue ſo great mageſtye and godly auctorite vnto the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiticall prohibicions / that they doo playnly affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me and hold ſtedfaſtly: that who ſo euer doith m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary contrary to the commandment of thies lawes be not (in ded) man and wife: nor they cannot rend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er one to the other the dewty of matrimony wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hout dedly ſyn: nor they can not be togither by any iugement of the churche / thus ſay the Popes / all this ys theſe deceyuers ſainge / and ſo with thies wordes &amp; ſaynges they wold ſwade and moue the reder to beleue that it is againſt the lawe of God / &amp; againſt the lawe of nature / for a man to marye his Brothers wife a widowe left without yſſew: &amp; that the Pope hath no power to diſpence vppon ſuche mariage / but this (as ye haue ſene prouyd
<pb facs="tcp:11164:32"/> before ys verey falſe: and where as they ſaye yow maye in maner ſe a hole comen aſſent and agrem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent of the hole churche / (the whiche they vnderſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>and to their opinion) this ys alſo falſe. For the h<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ole aſſent and agrement of the churche hath agr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eyd that the Pope maye diſpence vppon mariage betwene the brother and the brothers wife widow &amp;c. And conſequently that ſuche mariage is noth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er agaynſt the lawe of nature: for ells the hole ch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urche / and lernyd men of the Princes and Popes counſaill / wolde not haue conſentyd that he ſhuld haue diſpenced vppon ſuche mariage: if it had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne agaynſte the lawe of God / and againſte the law of nature / and thus you maye ſee / that thies perſons ſaynge is falſe / whiche is this. That y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hole aſſent of the churche doith affirme matrim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ony betwene the brother and the brothers wife / to be agaynſt the lawe of God and agaynſt the law of nature / But the hole church of Criſtendom ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th without reclamacion approued ſuche matrim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oney lefull and good: Where as thies perſons ſaye that the Popes them ſelue haue geuen greate ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geſtye and godly auctorite vnto the Leuiticall pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hibicions: thies perſons name verey often and reherſe their Leuiticall prohibicions in generall. But I wold ſee them name one prohibicion Leuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>icall / whiche doith forbide that a man may not m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary his brothers wyfe wydowe lefte wythe owte yſſew. This they ſhulde bringe of the Leuiticall lawe the whiche wolde doo them ſum ſeruice / and
<pb facs="tcp:11164:33"/> make well for their purpoſe: but this they cannot doo nor no man for them: for as I haue ſhewed you ſuche mariage is not forbiden in the leuitical law / and therfore yowe maye playnly ſee that to bryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge in the Leuiticall lawe / ys no thynge for theyr purpoſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the .xxxviij. leif of their boke / they ſaye finally to make an ende. Thow ſhalt vnderſtand gentill reader / that the requeſtis and ſuetes of diuerſe p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erſons / whiche haue deſyred diſpenſac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ions in thies degreys haue many tymes here to fo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re bene denyed and repellid by the Popes of Rome whiche anſwered them thus. It is not in any caſe leful for vs to diſpence with the lawes of God: a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d this we ſhall ſhewe yow here after. To this their reaſon and ſophiſtical argument / I anſwere that al thowghe ſum Popes haue denyed to diſpence in ſuche degreys of affinite: yet vppon this no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can conclude that therfore ſuche degre is of affini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te do ſet mariage by the lawe of God and by the l<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aw of nature. For the Pope may deny to diſpence in the thyrde degre of conſanguinite / and affinite in the ſide lyne / and yet euery man knowithe / th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at the thyrde degre of affinite and conſanguinite doith not let matrimony by the lawe of God / and by the law of nature / and alſo theyr argument ys nowght and ſophiſtical. Alſo the Pope maye leful<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly denye and not lycence a manis ſone to mary his
<pb facs="tcp:11164:33"/> fathers goddoughter / and yet ſuche mariage ys n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eyther forbidden by the lawe of God / nor by the l<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awe of nature / and thus yow may ſee / that thies perſons reaſon is no thinge worthe. Thei ſay / th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at you ſhal vnderſtande / that Popes hath deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to diſpence in ſuche degreys: And I ſaye that yowe ſhall vnderſtonde that Popes haue diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyd and lycencyd the Brother to marye the ſiſter and the ſon to mary the Fathers Siſter / and the Brother to mary the Brothers widowe / and one man to mary two Siſters / and alſo the ſame man to mary his wifes nece. And that Popes haue li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencyd moo perſons to marye in ſuche degreis of affinite and conſanguinite / as I ſhall ſhewe y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owe here after. Wherfore yowe maye percey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue thies deceyuers reaſon is of no ſtrength.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow where as they ſaye that the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes / whan they denyed to diſpence in ſuche degreys / they anſweryd thus. yt is not in eny caſe lefull for vs to d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſpence withe the Lawes of God / a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nd this thies perſons ſaye they will ſhewe here a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fter / and I wyll make anſwere vnto yt whan that they ſhewe it. Finally to make an ende: yow ſhall vnderſtand / that in the .xxxviij. leif of their boke / they make an Epilogacyon / And a gr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eat heape of ſhamefull lyes / ſaynge / Moreouer t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>how ſeeſt (and excepte we be deceyued) thow doiſt
<pb facs="tcp:11164:34"/> graunte &amp;c. I reherſe no more of their letter / beca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſe yow may ſee the reſidewe in their boke whiche ys all togither falſe / and ſo in the ende of their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond chapiter in the .xxxix. leif that maketh a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ncluſion of the ſame ſtuffe / ſayng / that the ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce and determinacyons of their vniuerſites is of as vndowtyd credence and auctorite / as can be. Where they ſaye / that to mary hir that is left of his brother dyinge without children / is ſo forbidd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en / both by the lawe of God / and by the law of na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture: that the Pope is not of power to diſpence wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th any ſuche maryage / whether they be all redy c<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ontracte / or ells to be contracte. This is the ſente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nce and determinacions of theyr vniuerſites: yet thies perſones (as ye haue ſene) haue not prouyd it / nother by auctorite / nor reaſon / nor they neuer ſhal / for the ſentence and the determinacions of t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heyr vniuerſites / ar manifeſt falſe and a great er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror hereticall: wherfore yf theſe perſons had ſayd that the ſentences and determinacions of the vni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerſites / be as vndowtid falſehed as can be / whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re they ſaye: That to mary hyr that is lefte of his brother dying without children / is ſo forbidden bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>the by the lawe of God / and by the lawe of natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re / and that the Pope is not of power to diſpence with any ſuche mariage / than they hade ſaid tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wth: for without faile / the ſentences and determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacions of theyr vniuerſites are vndowtid falſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hed / as yow haue partly harde / and as ye ſhal he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>are more / her after.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:11164:34"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the third chapiter in the .xxxix. le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>if of theyr boke / thei ſay thus. We th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inke that we haue wel and ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly confirmyd and ſtabiliſhed owr ent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and purpoſe by the Popes lawes / and by the auctorite and counſels. Nowe next we will go about to fortifye and make goode the ſame by the moſt excellent and moſt faithfull interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and moſt trew doctours that expownde holy ſcripture. Here they ſaye that they haue well and ſufficiently confirmid and ſtablyſſhed their entent by the Popes lawe and by the auctorite of counſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ls: And yet yow may ſee that they haue brought nether Popes law nor counſels that affirme thys theyr falſe purpoſe. That it is againſte the lawe of God / and againſte the lawe of nature / for a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to mary his brothers wife a widow &amp;c. And that the Pope hath no power to diſpence vppon ſuche mariage. Wherfore they ſhuld haue ſayd that th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ey hade nother well nor ſufficiently confyrmyd a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſtabilyſhed their purpoſe: nor yet neuer ſhal by no faithful interpreters and trew doctours that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pownde holy ſcripture / had thies perſones ſaid th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us / they had ſayd trowth. But that they loue to ſaye as theyr boke doith euidently ſhew / Nowe I beſeche you marke and note well what thies doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours ſaye that they bring in / and how well they f<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ortify thies deceyuers purpoſe. Firſt they bring in and allege the great clerke Origene / wher he exp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owndith the .xx. chapiter of the Leuitical. Now I
<pb facs="tcp:11164:35"/> beſeche yowe loke well vppon all that they bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nge of Origene / and yowe ſhall ſee that in noo poynte he helpith or favoryth their opinion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the .xli. leif of theyr boke / they ſay that Criſoſtom doith agre with Ori<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gen / and they ſay trewth / for he doith no thinge ſay that makithe for theyr purpoſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the .xlij. leif of theyr boke / they ſay that Baſilius the greate / ys of the ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ame ſentence and mynde / that thies other two forſayd doctours be / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d if yt be ſo / than he doith not fortyfye theyr opinion: for the other two doctours in no caſe fauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ur and affirme this thies perſons opinion. That it is agaynſte the law of God and agaynſte the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we of nature / for a man to mary his brothers wife a widow &amp;c. nor yet thies doctours do not ſaye th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at the Pope haith no power to diſpence vppon ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che mariage. Nor this can not be gatherid of thies doctours wordes nor conclude / as yow maye ſe in thies perſons boke / wher they allege thies docto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urs / and if this doctoure Baſilius be of the ſame ſentence and mynde / that Origene and Criſoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me be: than he helpith no thinge thies perſons opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion: and it is in dede trewth / for Baſilius in al his goodly piſtill doith not ſaye that it is agaynſte the lawe of God / and againſte the lawe of nature / for
<pb facs="tcp:11164:35"/> a man to mary his Brothers wyfe a widowe left without yſſewe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the .xliij. leif. they allege Baſilius agayn ſaynge / If it fortune a man to be ouercum with ſhameles and vncle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nly affeccion to ioyne ſo vnlefully / th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at he coupilith hym ſelf by mariage with two ſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers / this man is iuged not to haue contracte any mariage: And that he muſt not be admitted in to the communion of the churche / or cum in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of Criſten folke before that they haue brok<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en this ſo vnlefull couple or bonde / and be depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tid the on from the tother / To this ſaynge I anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer thus. That it is vnderſtand on this wiſe th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at if a man ouercomen with ſhameles affeccion / co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uplyth him ſelf by mariage with .ij. ſiſters witho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ut the Popes licence / that than he owght to be iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged not to haue contracte any mariage with the ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cond ſiſter: for by cauſe he did agaynſte the ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unce of the church: whiche hath decreyd that no man ſhall mary two ſiſters: and alſo if any man will attempte the contrary / and mary .ij. ſiſters: that than the couplynge withe the ſeconde Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter to be iuged no mariage: but rather the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rſons that ſo did couple them ſelues vnder the pretence of mariage agaynſte the lawe of the c<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hurche / not to be admitted in to the communion of the churche or cum emonge Chriſten people before that they haue broken theyr vnteafulle
<pb facs="tcp:11164:36"/> couple and bonde / and be departid the one from the tother. Thus on this wiſe all Baſilius ſaynge is trwthe / and makith againſt thies perſons pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe and opinion. But they ſhuld rather haue br<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ought (yf they hade coulde) Baſilius to haue ſaid that he / whiche couplyth hym ſelf to .ij. ſiſters o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne after the deth of the tother for honeſt reſpectis &amp; cauſes with the Popes lycence doith againſte the lawe of God / and agaynſte the lawe of nature / ſo that the Pope can not diſpence vppon ſuche mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iage. If thies perſones hade brought in this of ba<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſilius ſaynge / it wolde haue done them ſum ſeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ice. But they can not / and therfore Baſilius help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them nothynge.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the .xlviij. leife theſe perſons allege yſichyus / Gregorye Nazanzeus ſcol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ere an excellent lernyd man in holy ſc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ripture to be of Origens Chriſoſtome and of Baſilius ſide / for he expunding the Leuitical lawe ſaith thus &amp;ce. To this I anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>were / that yf yſichius be of the reherſed doctours ſyde / than it folowith that he ſaythe no thinge for to ayde thies deceyuers falſe opinion. For nether Origen Chryſoſtom nor Baſilius ſpeke no thing in to the fauour of thies perſons opinion. and thus Iſychius / being of the other doctours ſide / ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not helpe thies perſons opinion / nor he doith not helpe them in dede in no maner of point: as you may m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anifeſtly ſe in thies perſons boke / where they doo
<pb facs="tcp:11164:36"/> allege hym / for they allege hym where he expoun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dith the .xviij. Chapiter in the Leuiticall boke: where it is not forbidden that a man ſhal not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry his brothers wife a widowe lefte without yſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we. As I haue often tymes ſhewid yow: Nor Iſic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hius doith not ſay that ſuche mariage is ther for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden: nor he doith not ſaye that ſuche mariage is forbidden by the lawe of God and by the lawe of nature / nor yet he doith ſaye that the Pope haith no power to diſpence vppon mariage betwene the brother and the brothers wife a widowe left with out yſſewe. And therfore ye may perceue that Iſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chius doith nothing for thies deceuers purpoſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the .li. leif of their boke / they ſaye on this wiſe. Now with all thies doctours opinions agre ſaynte Ambroſe / ſaynte Hierome / and ſaynte Auſtyne. And firſt thies perſons allege ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynte Ambros where as he anſwereth to one Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erne which wold haue maryed his dowghters do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wghter vnto his owne ſoone: whiche ſon was the maydens half vncle. For Paterne the father had his ſone by an other woman / and in this caſe ſayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te Ambros ſayd thus. That the ſone myght not mary with the fathers dowghters dowghter / nor yete the nece with the nece / ſaynge that the lawe of God forbiddith that the ſone ſhulde mary with the brothers dowghter. This is now ſaynte Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe his mynde. To this I anſwere that expreſly we haue in the ſame lawe of God that ſaynte A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mbroſe
<pb facs="tcp:11164:37"/> ſpekith of: that the vncle maryed the ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce / and the nece maryed with the nece. As Othon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iel maryed his Brothers dowghter / which was c<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allid Axa: and the nece maryed with the nece / as the doughters of Salphat maryed with their vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cles ſones / <note place="margin">Nume. vltimo</note> and here no man can ſaye that thies p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erſons maryed theyr vncles ſones by a diſpenſaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and lycence of almyghtye God: for they were not lycencyd but commaundid by almyghty God ſo to mary / for ther was a law made and publyſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the reaſon of the dowghters of Salphat as the very texte here ſheweth. Reſpondit Moyſes filijs Iſrael &amp; domino precipiente ait: recte tribus filiorum Ioſeph loquuta eſt / &amp; hec lex ſuper fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liabus Salphat a Domino promulgata eſt / &amp; ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitur / fecerunt filie Salphat vt ſibi fuerat imp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eratum. And ſo thies women maryed their vncles ſones according to the lawe and commaundement of almyghty God / and ſo in lykwiſe / the dought<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of Eleazar maryed theyr vncles ſones.<note place="margin">i. Par. xxiij.</note> By t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>his you may ſe it is not forbiden by the law of god the ſone to marye withe the Brothers dowghter / nor the nece with the nece. but ſuche mariages w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ere commaunded by almyghty God in his lawe. Thies perſons ſaye in the .lij. leif / that ſainte am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe doith affirme to be againſt the law of nature for a man to mary his doughter. This is trew a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d noman will ſaye the contrary. but this ſaynge ys no thing for thies perſons purpoſe / let them ſhewe where ſaynte ambroſe ſaith. It is agaynſt the law
<pb facs="tcp:11164:37"/> of nature for a man to mary his brothers wif a w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>idow left without yſſewe. This thies deceyuers promiſe to ſhewe and brynge in / but they do not.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the .liiij. leif of their boke / they bry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nge in ſaynte Hierome that meruelyth at the Patriarke abraham for by cau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe he maryed his ſiſter: ſeing the thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge is ſo abhominable / and ſeynge ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ayne that almyghty God ordenyd afterward a l<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aw for it. wherin he thretenith that who ſo euer ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hal take his ſiſter / other on the fathers ſide / or on the mothers ſide: &amp; ſhal ſe hir fowlnes: yt is a rebu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke &amp; a ſhame / he ſhal be dryuen owt of his countre in ſight of his owne kynne: he haithe vnhilled the priuetes of his ſiſter / he ſhal receiue his reward for his ſynne. after this ſaing / thies deceuers make an expoſicion vpon ſainte Hieroms writing: &amp; for by<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cauſe yt is not to the purpoſe / I let it paſſe / thow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghe it be falſe / &amp; to ſaynte Hierome ſayng I anſw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ere thus. what ſo euer ſaynte Hierome ſaith wher they do allege him / I wolde ſhewe ye / that ſaynte Hierome doith not meruell nor iuge abrahams ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>riage to be euyl: but doith excuſe abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in that he maryd his ſiſter ſaynge / In the Hebrew tonge / yt ſoundith that Sara was abrahams ſiſter:<note place="margin">In q<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſti. hebrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per gen.</note> &amp; in his excuſe he ſayth that at that tyme ſuche mariage was not forbiden by the law. Here ye may ſe that ſainte Hierome doith excuſe the Patriarche abram in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he maryed his ſiſter: &amp; ſaith y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme of abra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11164:38"/> ſuche mariage was not forbidden by the lawe: the whiche muſt be vnderſtand / that ſuche mariage was not forbidden bi the lawe of nature. For yf th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at ſuche mariage had bene lefull and againſte the lawe of nature: than ſaynte Hierome had not iuſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyed and excuſed Abraham in that he maryed his ſiſter ſaynge: that ſuche mariages at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme were not foebidden by the lawe. And ſo thus nowe yow maye perceyue that Saynte Hieroms mynde and writinge here ys / that it is not agaynſte the lawe of nature for a man to mary his ſiſter. And ſo by this ſaynte Hierome is agaynſt thies perſones fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lſe opinion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the .lv. leif of their boke / thies perſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons brynge ſaynte Auguſten wher he writith againſte Fauſtus the greate heretik and ſaythe that the commau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ndment of God that bownde the iues to mary with theyr brothers wifes widowes lefte without yſſew / was a figure / and dyd ſignifie that the preachers ſhuld labour in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpell to ſtyre vp the ſead / vnto his brother departyd: that ys to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ur ſauiour Criſt / which died for vs. Here ye maye ſee that ſaynte Auſten ſaith that the commaund<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God that bownde the Iues to mary the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yr brothers wyues widows / was a figure / &amp; then it can not be againſte the lawe of nature: as to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer vp incenſe and to be circuncyſed were figurs / &amp; yet now they be not agaynſte the lawe of nature
<pb facs="tcp:11164:38"/> and thus Saynte Auguſtyn is not for theſe me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis purpoſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the .lvi. leif / They brynge in ſayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te Auguſtyn in an other place where as he ſaith. Althowghe in tyme paſt men maried thier ſiſters / yet that th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge was doen bycauſe neceſſite comp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ellid men vnto it / but this thinge is not now ſo ol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de / nor was neuer ſo necſſary: but it was made af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward as damnable / bicauſe religion doith forb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>idde yt. Thus here is the engliſſhe of ſaynte auſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens wordes / and after the ſame wordis that thies perſons haue in their Latyn boke. but they haue in theyr yngliſhe boke that it is not now as dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable / by cauſe religion doith forbide it / And ſayn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te Auſten ſaith is was made afterwarde as dam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nable / bycauſe religion doith forbide yt. And than yf this / for a man to mary his ſiſter be nowe made dampnable bycauſe religion doith forbide yt: Th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an it is euident that for a man to mary his ſiſter / is not damnable of the owne nature: for that thy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nge that is damnable by nature / was / and ys al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways dampnable. and ſaynte auguſten ſaith that this thyng / for a man to mary his ſiſter / was ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de afterward dampnable / becauſe religion doith f<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orbid yt: and therfore it is not agaynſt the lawe of nature for a man to mary his ſiſter: alſo ſaynte a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uguſtyn ſaith in the ſame place where thies perſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons allege hym / that in the begynninge of man k<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynde
<pb facs="tcp:11164:39"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> was leful by al meanys y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> brothern to mary wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſiſters: but now (ſaith he) y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cuſtom ys ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e mariage as thoughe ſiche mariage h<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>er ben lawfull. By this ye may ſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> for a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to mary his ſiſter / is leful by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law of nature: &amp; it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>den <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e cuſtome: &amp; than yt folowith that yf ſuche <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e be lefull by the lawe of nature / it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y the ſame lawe for a man to mary h<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s wife a widowe lefte withowt yſſewe. For this can be no more forbiden than for a man to marye his Siſter. And thus yowe maye perce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yue that ſainte auguſtyn is againſt thies perſons falſe opinion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the ſame leif / thies perſons wold h<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aue yow call to yowr rememberaunce of the iugement of thies great diuines fower / or fyue thinges. Firſt what ſo euer perſone of Criſtes beleue brekith eny of the le<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uiticall prohibicions of mariage / he ſhal be damp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned both body and ſowle into euerlaſtinge deith in hell. Note here I beſeche ye how thies peſtilent p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erſons openly ſclaunder and ſaye falſe vpon ſain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te ambroſe / ſainte Hierome / and ſainte Auguſtin. For ther is none of them that doith iuge / that wh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at ſo euer perſon of Criſtes beleue brekith eny of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leuiticall prohibicions of mariage that he ſhall be dampned bothe body and ſowle into euerlaſtinge deith in hell / as thies perſons do ſaye vppon them but it is thies 'peſtilent perſons owne malicious
<pb facs="tcp:11164:39"/> iugement: and yet all this makith nothing for th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eir falſe opinion. For ther is no prohibicion leuitic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al that doith forbide that a man ſhal not mary h<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is brothers wife a widowe &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ſecond thinge that thei wolde ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue yow note of the iugement of ſainte ambroſe / ſainte Hierome / and ſainte auguſtin is this. That not only the Iues did abſtaine frome marying th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eir Brothers wiues euen as yow wold ſay / for fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re of ſum miſchef / and yet thei might haue don it bi auctorite of their law: but the very heythens al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo after the deth of their wiues / did euermore abſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine frome mariage of their wiues ſiſtern / as fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me a certain impiete or abominacion againſte nat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ure. Here thies ſhameles perſons falſly ſclaunder againe thies holy Doctours / for they neuer did iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge nor ſaye that the Iues did abſtayne frome ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryinge of their Brothers wiues for fere of ſum m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yſchefe that ſhulde fall vppon them / for ſo mary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge. Nor yet thies holy men neuer ſayde that the heythens did euermore abſteyne from maryi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nge their wiues ſiſterne / as frome a certaine impi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ete or abhominacion againſte nature. Wherfore yowe maye ſee that theſe vngracious perſons do falſly ſaye and ſclaunder Sainte Ambroſe / Sai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nte Hierome / and Sainte Auguſtin / and not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in this their falſe ſainge ſclaunder theſe holy men / But they alſo doo blaſpheme almightye
<pb facs="tcp:11164:40"/> God: for in ſaynge that the Iues did abſteyne fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me mariynge their Brothers wifes for fere of ſum myſcheif that ſhuld fal vppon them for ſo mariy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nge / they ſaye that almyghty God in commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge and biddinge the Iues to mary theyr broth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers wifes widowes &amp;cet. commaundid and bounde them to a thinge that myſchefe ſhulde cum to the Iues for fullfillinge and kepyng of the ſame com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement / ye and beſide all this yt followithe that almyghty God in commaunding and biddi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nge the Iues to mary their Brothers wifes wido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ws &amp;cet. ſet the Iues in a myſerable ſtate and in a greuous perplexite / for yf they maryd theyr brot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hers wifes widows &amp;c. accordynge to the comma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>undinge of almyghty God: than they lokyde for myſchef to fall vppon them for ſo mariynge, and agayne / if they did not marry their brothers wifes widowes &amp;c. than they ſhulde be punyſhed withe perpetuall infamy and diſhonour. For ſo had alm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yghty God commaundid to punyſhe all thos th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at wold not mary their brothers wyfes widowes &amp;c. and thus by thies falſe deceyuers ſaynges al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God in commaundinge the Iues to mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ye their brothers wifes widows &amp;cet. ſet them in a meruelous greuous perplexite. Who durſt thus ſaye by almyghty God / ſeynge that he noureſſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Iues with ſingler beneuolence and meruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous kynenes holy and iuſte lawes concerning them and theyr tyme? Wherfore yowe maye ſee thies perſons in theyr ſayng do highly baſpheme almy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghty
<pb facs="tcp:11164:40"/> God: and do falſly ſaye vppon thies holy men and Doctours.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow to the ſeconde parte of this their ſecond ſaynge / wher as thies perſons affirme that the verey heythens aft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er the deth of theyr wiues did euermo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re abſtayne frome mariynge of theyr wyues ſiſters as fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a certayn impiete or abomin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acion againſt nature. Here thies deceyuers confo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unde them ſelues and ſpeke againſte their owne writinge. For in the .xviij. leif of their boke / they ſaye: that beſide other myſcheuous vices this th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge was alſo lefull and cuſtomable amonge th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ies haythens to myngle and marcy them ſelf by the moſt ſhameful luſt and pleaſure of their bod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yes with them that be moſt nyghe of their blode and affinite puttinge no difference betwene them and other women. This they ſayd and write th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ere / and here they ſaye the contrary. They ſaye that the heythens after the deth of theyr wiues d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>id euermore abſtayne frome mariynge of their w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iues ſiſters as frome a certayne Impiete or abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minacion againſt nature: Therfore yow may cl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eerly ſe / thies perſons be paſt ſhame / and care not whate they write and ſaye / that they myght cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe the reder to beleue their falſe opinion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He thirde thinge that thies deceyuers w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olde haue yow note of the iugement of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynte
<pb facs="tcp:11164:41"/> Ambroſe / ſaynte Hierome / and ſaynte Auſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en is this. That mariage contracte contrary to t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heis prophibicions be vncomely and abhominable and as nere as can be to the lyfe of bruyt beſtis &amp;c. ye and forther / thei be the tranſgreſſion a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d breking of al the lawe. Here theſe falſe lyers ſaye agayne falſly on theſe holy men. For this they can not ſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ew to be the iugement of Saynte Ambros / Sainte Hierome / and Saynte Auguſten. Alſo thies lyes and falſe ſaynges make no thinge for their purp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſe. For they ſpeke of the leuiticall lawe and there ground the them ſelf: wher it is in no wiſe forbiden that a man ſhal not marey his brothers wife a w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>idowe left without yſſew.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He .iiij. thinge that thies deceyuers wolde haue yow to note and marke of the iugement of ſaynte Ambroſe ſaynte Hierome / and ſaynte Auſten is this / That mariages made cont<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rary to the leuitical prohibicions be ſo greuous a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſo hateful in the ſight of God / that thei haue deſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>royd holl nacions / poluted the land / and beyng po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutyd cauſed it naturally to gruge and to put them owt whiche hade committed ſuche thinges. Here agayn theis deceyuers ſaye falſly vppon thies ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men: for thei cannot ſhew thies their ſayngis to be thies doctours iugement. Alſo thies lyes and f<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alſe ſaynges make no thing for thies perſons fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe purpoſe: for al their ſaynge ys grownded in the
<pb facs="tcp:11164:41"/> Leuiticall lawe: and there yt is not forbidden that a man ſhall not marey hys Brothers wife a wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe left without yſſewe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He .v. thing that thies perſons wolde haue yow note of the iugement of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynte Ambroſe / ſainte Hierome / and ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ainte Auſten is this. That the prohi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bicions leuiticall perteyne not only to theiues / but to all Criſtians whiche cum to ſerue God. And that thei which be poluted with eny of thies not to be ſpoken dedis / ar defilyd with them al. Here thies ſhameles lyers ſaye falſly on Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe / Hierome / and Auſten: for as I haue ſhewid yow / they cannot bringe where that this their ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng ſhuld be thies holy menys iugementis. and agayne this their falſe ſayng doith not helpe thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es deceyuers falſe opinion / as you haue hard befo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re / by cauſe they grownd them in the leuitical pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibicions: But now for aſmuche as in this their ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aing / thei affirme y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> if a man be polutid &amp; corrupte with eny of thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s not to be ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dedis / he is defy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al: he<hi rend="sup">r</hi> ye may ſe how like the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelf thei ſpeke / for of this their ſaing / it folowith y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> if a man<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly with his ſiſt<hi rend="sup">r</hi> &amp; ſo is polutid in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſyn: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> than he is poluted with his moth<hi rend="sup">r</hi> / with his ſtepmoth<hi rend="sup">r</hi> / w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ith his doughter / poluted with his nece / &amp; with b<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruet beſtis / polutid with offering his ſede in ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ydol Moloch. For al thies &amp; oth<hi rend="sup">r</hi> mo / be for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leuitical law: who wold ſay thꝰ but thies filthy &amp; lying
<pb facs="tcp:11164:42"/> perſons? Nowe yowe hard howe thies deceyuers haue ſclaundered and falſly ſayd of thies .iij. holy men ſaynte Ambroſe / ſainte Hierome / and ſainte Auguſtin.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the .lvij. leif / they exhorte yowe to marke wel ſaynte Ambroſe his ſaynge / and to that yow haue herd my anſwere before.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter thies doctours thies perſons b<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe holy ſaynte Ancelme. Breifly he in all that piſtel / which thies per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſaye is his / doith not ſaye that it is againſt the lawe of God and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the lawe of nature / for a man to mary his brothers wife a widowe &amp;ce. nor yet this that the Pope haith no power to diſpence vppon ſuche ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage: nor this can not be gatheryd nor concludid of this ſaynge of ſaynte Ancelme in the reherſed pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle as it appereth in the .lx. leif of their boke. T<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hat Criſtiane religion and perfeccion haith ordyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that the boundis and butailes of conſanguinite ſhulde be ſtreched furthe vnto the .vi. degre on eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ery ſide / accordinge vnto the decreys of holy fath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and canons: ſo that kynſfolke beyng in the .vi degre maye not marey toghither: by this you may ſe that ſainte Ancelme doith ſpeke of ſuche maria<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge as is forbiden bi the lawe of the churche: and t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herfore in the ende of his piſtel he ſhewith that b<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>othe before the law and in the law / men vpon cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb facs="tcp:11164:42"/> honeſt cauſes and conſideracions maried t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heir nere knſwomen / as their ſiſters and their ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: before the lawe / as Abraham / Iſaac / and Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob. In the law / Othoniel / the whiche mariages ſainte Ancelme doith not ſaye that thei were aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inſt the lawe of nature. But he doith approue th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>em good: for bicauſe the perſons which ſo maryed / did marey for good conſideracions and honeſt cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes / yet for all that (ſaith he) Criſtiane religion &amp; the perfytnes that owght to be in a Criſten man wil iuge nothinge to be honeſt that is againſt the honeſtie of nature. So here ſainte Ancelme doith ſwade that we ſhuld not mary nowe owr kinneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>women / but mary other for to ſpreyd a brode loue and charite / for it is againſt the honeſtye of natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re aftir his mynde / to mary within the .vj. degre. For men and women do bi the reaſon of affinite &amp; kindred bare loue naturally vnto that degre. And therfore ſainte Ancelme did extende the honeſtie of nature to the .vi. degre / as it aperith bi his ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nge before / And thus yow may ſe that ſainte an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celme doith not ſaye that it is againſte the law of nature for a man to mary his ſiſter and nere ky<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nſwoman: but that for honeſte cawſes men ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue ſo maryed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the .lxv. leif / thies perſons bring in Hughe Cardinal: Rauffe Flamacen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis / Rute Tintienſis / Hildebart Ce<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nomaneſe / Iuo Carnotenſe / al biſhops
<pb facs="tcp:11164:43"/> and one water of conſtance archedeacon of Oxfor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de / and truly the firſt two Hughe Cardinal / and Rauffe flauiacenſis expoundinge the xviij. chapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter leuitical. Brefely here I anſwere / there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne of thies Doctours that ſaith it is againſte the law of God and againſte the lawe of nature / for a man to m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ry his brothers wife a widow left wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hout yſſew: nor yet this that the Pope haith no p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ower to diſpence vpon ſuche mariage: nor this can not be concludid of their ſaynges. Wherfore I paſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe ouer vnto the .lxxv. leif of thies deceyuers boke where they allege for their purpoſe the ſcholaſtic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all doctours.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow amonge the ſcolaſtical doctours thies perſons do bringe in Thomas in the .lxxviij. leyf of their boke: whiche ſaith that at the beginning of mank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inde there were exceptid frome maria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge the father and the mother / that is to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand / that the father myght not marey with the doughter / nor the mother with the ſoon / but after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward when mankynde was encreaſide and multi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>plied there were many moo perſons excepte bi M<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oyſes lawe. Brefely ſaynte Thomas in all hys reaſons before and after doith no thinge but decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re that the father and the dowghter / the mother and the ſoon were forbiden to mary togither bi the lawe of nature. The oth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r perſons that were aft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erward except / he ſaith were forbiden to mary to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither
<pb facs="tcp:11164:43"/> by the lawe of Moyſes: whiche law / Th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>omas callith ſum tyme the lawe of God. This maye yowe ſee plainly in al the proceſſe that thies perſons do bringe in of Thomas from the .lxxv. leif / vnto the .lxxix. leif / and thus Thomas ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth not one worde againſt this that a man maye mary his brothers wife a widowe lefte withowte yſſew / nor yet againſte this / that the Pope haithe power to diſpence vpon ſuche mariage.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hies perſons promiſed to bring doctou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rs to ſpeke againſte thies thinges: but they be verey ſlake in performinge th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eir promeſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the ſame leife / thies perſons doo b<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in Thomas ſayng / infidels cont<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racte within the degreis forbiden in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> xviij. Chapiter of Leuitical / contrary to the lawe of God: whether both to or one of them be conuertid to the faith: they maye not bide ſtill togither in ſuche mariage: for as my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che as ſaynte Thomas ſpeketh here of the degre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ys forbiden in the .xviij. chapiter of the leuitical: I wil anſwere no other wiſe but thus / yt is not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biden in the .xviij. Chapiter of the leuiticall that a man ſhal not mary his brothers wife a widowe left with out yſſew: and therfore ſaynte Thomas ſpekith nothinge for thies deceyuers purpoſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:11164:44"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lſo to Altiſſiodorenſis ſaynge / wh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ere thei allege him to ſaye that the preceptis Leuitical be moralles: this ſaynge doith no ſeruice to thies dec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eyuers falſe opinion. For as I haue ſhewid you / and am compellid often tymes to ſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ew yow / that it is not forbiden in the Leuitical la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we that a man ſhal not mary his brothers wife a widow left without yſſew. And if thies deceiuers were not paſte ſhame they wolde not allege ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the leuitical lawe and prohibicions as they do ſeyng it makith nothinge for their purpoſe / or ells they ſhuld reherſe ſum prohibicion leuiticall that doith forbede that a man ſhal not mary his Brot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hers wife a widowe left &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the .lxxxij. leif / thei bringe Peter de Palude: whiche ſaith the Pope hathe no power to diſpence in the firſt degre of affinite no more than he haith in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt degre of conſanguinite: for maria<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geis forbiden bi the lawe of God in the firſt degre of conſanguinite or affinite not one ſtreghter abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue the other: but the one of ſyde half to the other as the brother and the ſiſter in this degre. Alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pope hath power to diſpence bycauſe it is ſumwh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at againſt the lawe of nature / and a litle after th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is Docter Peter de Palude ſaith that the Pope h<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ath no power to diſpence that a man ſhulde mary the wife of his brother althowgh he died without
<pb facs="tcp:11164:44"/> children / for how be it men were ſufferde to do th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us in tymes paſt: yet that was not but by diſpenſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acion / ye and that diſpenſacion was by the lawe of God and not by the lawe of men / and agayne a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle after this he ſaith that the Pope hath no more power to diſpence with a man to mary his brothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rs wife a widow left without yſſew / than he hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th to diſpence for a pluralite of wiues. For maria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge betwene the brother and the brothers widowe left without yſſewe: was ſufferd for a certayn ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me by the diſpenſacion of almyghty God / like as it was to haue many wifes. Here is this Doctou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rs mynde whiche ſpekith ſum what for thies perſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons purpoſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow to this Doctours ſaynge I anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>were thus / and firſt to this pointe w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here he ſaith that the Pope hath no p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ower to diſpence in the firſt degre of af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>finite no more than he hath in the firſt degre of conſanguinite and that not only in the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght lyne no more than in the ſide lyne: as the brot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>her to mary with the ſiſter: for by cauſe this is ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mwhat againſt the lawe of nature. To this / this Doctour Peter de Palude expownding the .xviij. Chapiter of the leuitical ſaith: that the Pope m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aye diſpence in al the degreis of affinite conteyned in the leuiticall / for al thies degreys (ſaith he) ſeme to be forbidden bi the lawe poſytiue. And now yow maye ſee by this doctours mynde that mariage be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene
<pb facs="tcp:11164:45"/> the brothers widowe and the Brothere / ys not againſt the lawe of nature: for this doctour ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aith that the Pope maye diſpence in that degre of affinite. and where as he ſayd that the Pope cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lde not diſpence that a man ſhuld mary his broth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers wife a widowe left without yſſewe: here he ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ith the contrary. For he ſaith the Pope may diſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nce in al degreis of affinite that be conteyned in t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>he leuiticall lawe. Alſo where as he ſaid that the Pope hath no more power to diſpence with a man to marey hys Brothers wyfe a widowe left with owt yſſewe / than he hath to diſpence for a plural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ite of wyfes: here yowe maye ſee that this Docto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ur ſaith the contrarey. For he affirmeth that the Pope maye diſpence in all degreys of affinite cont<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eyned in the Leuiticall lawe. And finally where as he ſaith / that it was ſuffered for a certayne tyme that the brother ſhulde mary the Brothers wyfe a widowe left withowte yſſewe / but this he ſayth was but by the diſpenſacion of almyghty God: li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke as it was to haue many wifes. This ſaynge can in no caſe be trew: for almighty god did not deſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pence in the olde law / that a man might mary his Brothers wife a widowe left without yſſewe: but did expreſly commaund that al the Iues ſhuld al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways marey their brothers wifes widowes lefte withowt yſſewe. And they ſhuld ſo mary vppon a great payne. And therfore it is not trew to ſaye that almyghty God did diſpence withe the Iues that they might mary their Brothers wifes wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owes
<pb facs="tcp:11164:45"/> left without yſſewe / for thei were bownde to mary their Brothers wifes left withoute yſſewe / by an expreſſid lawe of almyghty God / alſo this can in no wyſe be callid a diſpenſacion: for a diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacion doith alwayes preſuppoſe a commaundm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent contrary to the lycenſe and diſpenſacion: but in all the hole lawe ther is no commaundement th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at forbiddeth that a man ſhal not mary his Brot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hers wife a widowe lefte with owte yſſewe: as it is manifeſte. Wherfore it can not be ſayd that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myghty God did diſpence and licence the Iues to mary theyr Brothers wifis widowes lefte withe owte yſſewe. Finally by licence and diſpenſacion a man is ſet at libertye to vſe his diſpenſacion or not to vſe it: but the Iues were not at libertie and at choyſe to marey their brothers wifes widowes le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fte withe owte yſſewe / or ellis to leue them. But rather the lawe compellid the Iues to m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arey theyr Brothers wifes widowes lefte wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>he owte yſſewe. or ells to punyſhe ſuche as w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>old not marey their Brothers wifes widowes lefte without yſſewe / with perpetuall infamy and great diſhoner. Wherfore it can not be ſayd that almyghty God did diſpence withe the Iues to m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arey theyr Brothers wyfes widowes lefte withe owt yſſewe / but he commaundid them ſo to marey The example alſo and ſimilitude that this doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Peter de Palude brought to ſhewe that almy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghty God did diſpence withe the Iues that they might mary their brothers wifes widows &amp;c. doith
<pb facs="tcp:11164:46"/> not proue in eny caſe. He ſaith on this wiſe that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God ſuffered the Iues to mary their bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wifes widowes &amp;c. lyke as he did ſuffer ſum perſons to haue mo wifes at ons than one. This ſaynge is not like: for the firſt / almyghty God did commaund / and bounde euery man to it: but the ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cond / that a man myght haue mo wifes at ons th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an one / almyghty God did neuer commaunde to perſons in general nor in ſpecial: and ſo yow maye ſee that the exemple and ſimilitude doith not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue. Here parauenture ſum will meruyll at this d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>octour Peter de Palude whiche in expowndinge the lawes leuitical doith ſo directly ſpeke againſte that he wrote in his boke vppon the ſentences. To this it may be anſweryd that whan he wrote vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the ſentences he helde that opinion: but when he cam afterward and wolde expounde the leuiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call / he forſoke his opinion / whiche he helde befo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re: and here vppon the leuiticall boke he wrote y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trewthe: wherfore vppon the .xviij. chapiter leui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical he ſaith thus. In certayne bokes it is writen / no man maye take his brothers wife whiche (ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th he) is thus vnderſtand. No man maye take his brothers wife (his brother beynge a lyue) for aſm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uche as the lawe in a nother place doith commau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nde that a man ſhal mary his brothers wife a w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>idowe. And now by this ſaynge / this Doctour p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eter de Palude is not onely againſt the deceyuers opinion in many pointis as ye haue ſene before: but here alſo he vtterly doith deſtroye all the grounde
<pb facs="tcp:11164:46"/> where on thies perſons wolde bilde their falſe opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion. For he ſaith that the prohibicion leuitical th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at forbiddithe a man to take his brothers wife ys vnderſtande / to forbide him that he taketh not h<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is brothers wife while his brother is a lyue / for aſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>much as in an other place the lawe doith comma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>und that a man ſhal mary his brothers wife a w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>idow. Thus ye may perceue that this their great Doctour Peter de Palude doith vtterly deſtroye al thies deceyuers falſe opinion / for he ſhewith and affirmith that for a man to mary his brothers w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ife a widow / ys not forbiden in the leuitical lawe but he ſaithe ſuche mariage is commaundid in a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nother place of the lawe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the .lxxxiij. leif of their boke / thies perſons bringe in the auctorite of the byſhop of florens and Iohne de Turre cremata whiche (as thies perſones do ſay / do agre in this matter with Pet<hi rend="sup">r</hi> de Palude / n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ow if yt be ſo / than they ſpeke directly againſt the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ir falſe opinion: for Peter de Palude ſpekith agai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nſt yt / And if theſe deceyuers wil ſaye that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chbiſhope of florens and Iohn de Turre cremata doith agre with Peter de Palude / wher he did er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re / and not where he ſayd trewth. than ſuerly th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ey ſhuld noth<hi rend="sup">r</hi> be beleuid nor accept. Breuely thies two reherſed Doctours and Alexander de Ales whoſe ſaynge and opinion thies deceyuers do not recyte / they al grownde them in Peter de Palud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des
<pb facs="tcp:11164:47"/> firſt opinion / whiche he him ſelf did after forſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ake and reproue / and in the prohibicions leuiticall to the whiche I haue anſwered often tymes that it is not forbiden there that a man ſhal not marey his brothers wife a widowe left witheout yſſewe / and likewiſe doith the Doctours that they bringe after the ſayd Cardinals and Walden that ſaith the Leuitical lawes be morall preceptis and of the x. commaundements and that euen to ſo many d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>egreys as be rekennyd vp ther vnto the fower<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the / this vnto the fowerthe / theſe deceyuers leue owt of Waldens ſaynge: thowghe this opinion of Walden be falſe / yet I wold not tarry vpon it / nor vppon Pope martines approuinge of Waldens boke / nor yet vpon the Doctours whiche thei na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me without eny reherſinge of their writinges and opinions. For all thies be impertinent to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe as euery man may ſee in theſe deceyuers boke Wherfore I paſſe ouer to the .lxxxvii. leif.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the .lxxxvij. leif / thies perſones doo allege two gloſers of the lawe of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non / Iohn Andre and Iohn Imola w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hich do gather and conclude by the w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordes of the very texte of the chapiter Literas: and alſo bi the wordis of gloſes there / that the degreys writen in the leuiticall lawe be the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me ſelf degreis in the whiche Pope innocent hym ſelf doith ſaye that the Pope hath no power to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence with. Here thies perſons ſaye falſly of Iohn
<pb facs="tcp:11164:47"/> Andre: for in the ende of his anſwere he concludith that the Pope may diſpence in the firſt degre of c<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onſanguinite after that the matromony be ons co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummat / thus ye may ſe how thies ſhamles perſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons doo lye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the .lxxxviij leif / thei ſay y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> maiſter Abbot is of Iohn andres opinion: &amp; he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re alſo thei ſay falſely vpon Maiſter abbot / for he ther reherſinge diuers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions / finally doith conclude y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pope may diſp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in the firſt degre of affinite after y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> matrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny be conſummate. Thus ye may ſe that thies fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lſe deceyuers do not ceaſſe to lye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .lxxxix. leif / thies perſons ſay y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> to tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe perſons which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law of god doith cal ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of blode / ther can be no good nor iuſte cau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which it might be ſufferd or diſpenſed with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhuld diſkou<hi rend="sup">r</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fowlnes of a nother / nor the<hi rend="sup">r</hi> can not be alleged anything ſo honeſte / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is able to cov<hi rend="sup">r</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diſhoneſty of this thing. This is y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our own peſtilent ſaynge: here they greatly accuſe Abra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / Iſaac / &amp; Iacob: for thei maryd with their ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtern &amp; with their vncles doughters / &amp; if ther can not be allegid eny thing ſo good &amp; honeſte / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is able to couer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diſhoneſtie of ſuche mariages / than thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es perſons do condempne thies holy patriarkes / &amp; ſay y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in mariyng their kinneſwomen thei did ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mfully / &amp; euen y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thing which is ſo euyl y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ther can not be alleged eny thinge ſoo honeſte that is able
<pb facs="tcp:11164:48"/> to couer the diſhoneſtye of their Mariages. Who will ſaye thus by thies holy fathers and patriar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s / but thies vngracious perſons? Sainte Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rom doith excuſe Abraham in that he maryed his ſiſter / and ſhewith that in ſo mariynge he did not offend / as ye haue harde before. And ſainte auſten againſt Fauſtus the manachye / ſhewith that Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob did not offende in maryinge of his vncles dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghter / and ſaynte ancelme in the epiſtle / that thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es perſons affirme to be his / ſayth that for certain conſideracions and honeſt cauſes / men ſum tyme maryed their nere kynſwomen both before the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we and in the lawe / before the lawe / as abraham / and Iſaac / and Iacob / in the lawe / as Othoniel / thies holy men iuge thies mariages to be honeſte / iuſte / and goode: whiche thies vngracyous perſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ones do falſely dampne for to coloure their damp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable opinion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the .lxxxx. leif / of their boke thies p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erſones wold haue yow to marke ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially / which diuerſe of thies holy and approbate doctours do holde / alſo that the brother can not mary a woman t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hat is but only handfaſte vnto his brothere: and if he doo: the mariage can not ſtande by helpe of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny diſpenſacion / and that al ſuche mariages muſt nedes be vtterly broken / Of this opinion thies per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſones ſaye is mayſter lyre / and alſo the noble diui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne Hugh de ſancto victore. and ſo in the .lxxxxij.
<pb facs="tcp:11164:48"/> leif of their boke / they ſaye that mariage in the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rſte degre of conſanguinite and of affinite is not on<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly forbiden in the leuitical lawe: but alſo mariage in the firſt degre / for a iuſtice groundid only vppon a certain comyn honeſte and comelines / is forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den by the lawe of God in the leuitical: and ſo can not be diſpenſid with all by me. Here ye may ſe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we openly and without all ſhamfaſtnes they lye they bid yow marke whiche diuerſe of the holy a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d approbate Doctours do hold that the brother can not mary a woman that is but only handfaſte to his brother after his dethe (thus they muſte vnd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erſtande yt) and if a man doo: the mariage can not ſtande by helpe of eny diſpenſacion. Firſt thies pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rſons haue brought no doctoure that this doith af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>firme / and ther is nether maiſter Lyre / nor Hughe de ſancto Victore that doith ſaye that the pope can not diſpence with a man that he maye mary that woman whiche was only but handfaſt to his bro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>th<hi rend="sup">r</hi> aft<hi rend="sup">r</hi> his broth<hi rend="sup">r</hi>s deth. Hugo de S. vic. in al his longe proceſſe that thies perſons bring in / hath n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ot a worde of the Popes power and diſpenſacion / nor maiſter Lyre in this caſe / moreouer yt is euid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent that it is but only forbiden by the lawe of the churche that a man may not mary his brothers ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pouſe after the dethe of his brother. ther is no ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture nor Doctour ſaynge that ſuche mariage ys forbiden by the leuitical lawe / nor agayne ther is no Doctour that doith ſaye that the Pope can not diſpence in this caſe. yow may ſe what perſons be
<pb facs="tcp:11164:49"/> thies / thei care not howe falſly thei ſaye / thei be n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ot aſhamid to ſpeke agaynſt al reaſon and lerning</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or to proue their a fore reherſed ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nge / thei bring in a caſe: that ther was a man whiche had his eldeſt ſoon ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nd faſt to a mayde / and ſo this yonge men died: and than his father bounde him ſelfe by an other to the mayden / that he wold marey his yongeſt ſone to hyr / and vppon this / he made ſuyte to the Pope whiche was Alexandre y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thirde: and he wolde not diſpence and lycence this mannis yonger ſone to marey the maiden: but lete the man that ſwore he wolde mary his yonger ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one to the mayden be pariuride: where vppon thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es perſons wold conclude / that the Pope can not diſpence that a man maye mary his Brothers ſp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſe after his brothers dethe / which is falſe: for t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>his argument ys nought to ſaye. The Pope will not diſpence vppon ſuche mariage: wherfore it fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowith that he can not diſpence vppon ſuche ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage. This yow ſe doith not folowe. For the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe doith not alwais diſpence where he may diſpen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce. Alſo if the Pope were bounde to diſpence in the thyrde and fowerth degre of affinite withe euery man that did or wolde ſwere to mary in thies deg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reis / than the prohibicion were no prohibicion / Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo where as thies perſones ſaye that the Pope al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exandre did affirme in his anſwere to the Biſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe of Papye / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> it is writen in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leuitical / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Brot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>her
<pb facs="tcp:11164:49"/> can not haue the Brothers ſpouſe / and the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>for he commaundid the biſhope that he ſhulde not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fer henry that hath ſworne to mary his yonge ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the maide to fulfill his purpoſe. To this I anſwere that it is not forbidden in the Leuitical l<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aw that a man ſhal not mary his brothers ſpou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe: nor there is no maner of mencion made of eny ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uche mariage / and ſo ye may ſee that all that euer thei bring / ys not for their falſe purpoſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the .lxxxxiij. leif of their boke / vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their vndowted fals lyes and ſayng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is / thei wold thus conclude their falſe purpoſe ſayng. Wherfor ſeyng that t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hies thinges be thowghte trewe to ſo many and diſcrete auctours that it is not leful for a man to marey his brother ſpouſe: how much m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ore vnlawful owght we to thinke this thing / th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at a man ſhuld mary his brothers wife a widowe with whome his brother hath had carnally to do and that he ſhuld vncouer the priuites of hir &amp; cet. Here agayn they continew in their cuſtomable ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. For thei ſay y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> many diſcrete auctours haue iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ged y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is forbiden in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leuitical law y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a man ſhal not mary his brothers ſpowſe: &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſuche mariage is ſo vnleful / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pope can not diſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it. Th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is ye ſe is manifeſtly falſe: for ther is no diſcrete a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uctor that ſo ſaith / &amp; if ther be eny auctores y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſo iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge: why do not theis perſons bring them in? but t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hey ſaye verey falſly: for ther be no diſcrete aucto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that ſo iuge and ſaye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:11164:50"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Herin this their ſayng thei wolde h<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aue men to iuge &amp; beleue that it is v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nlawful for a man to mary his brot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hers ſpowſe. And than muche more vnlawful for a man to mary his br<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>others widowe with whome his brother hath ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de carnally to doo &amp;c. Here thies falſe deceyuers ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peke couertly. but I wil ſhewe yow a verey treu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th / whiche is this. The Quenis grace that now is / was a mayden when hir grace was maryed l<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſte / and in witnes and recorde that this is trewe hir grace haith ſworne / and teſtyfyed vppon a b<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oke and receyued the bleſſid Sacrament of the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter / that ſhe was a mayden when hir grace was laſt maryed. Wherfore the determinacions of the facultye of diuinite and the canon of the vniuerſite of Paryſe (thoughe that thei be falſe) yet they m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ake nothing againſt this matrimony / nor the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminacions of both the facultes of lawe / of thu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſite of Angew. nor the determinacion of diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite of the vniuerſite o Biturs / for thies haue det<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ermined on this wiſe: That if ther were paſte be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene the huſband and the wife / carnal copulaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: that than the brother / may not marey his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers widowe: nor the Pope can not diſpence vpon ſuche mariage / ſo now thowgh the determinacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of thies vniuerſites be falſe / as be al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> oth<hi rend="sup">r</hi>: yet th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ies reherſide / helpe no thing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peſtile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; malicious purpoſe of thies peſtilent ꝑſons: for aſmuche as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Quenis grace was a mayden / when ſhe was laſt maryed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:11164:50"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ere now ye haue harde parte of thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es ſhameles perſons maners: parte of their manifeſte errours / parte of their dampnable lyenge: and parte of their blaſphemy / yow haue alſo herde how that thei haue brought in holy ſcripture / counſels and doctours for to haue coloured and fortified th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eir vngracious and falſe opinion: and yet thei can not bringe it to paſſe nor neuer ſhal. Wherfore / al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thowghe in the beginninge of this my anſwere I ſhewid and prouid ſufficiently the trewthe of this propoſicion. That it is not againſt the law of god nor againſt the law of nature / for a man to marey his brothers wife a widowe left without yſſewe. And that the pope haith no power to diſpence vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon ſuche mariage: now yet / I wil ſhewe yow the ſame more largely by holy fathers / doctours / and Popes ſaynges / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d firſt that ſuche mariage is not agaynſt the law of nature.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt ſainte Hierome doith excuſe Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raham / in that he maryed his ſiſter / &amp; doith iuſtifye and defende Abraham for ſo mariynge.<note place="margin">In q<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt. heb. ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per gen.</note> For ſuche mariages ſaith ſaynte Hierome / were not than forbiden of the law of nature. And if it be not forb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iden bi the lawe nature a man to marey his ſiſter: miche leſſe was it forbiden / a man to marey his b<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rothers widowe left without yſſew.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:11164:51"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Aynte Auſten ſaith y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme of Abrah<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am / men might lefully mary with their ſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſters of the one ſide:<note place="margin">co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. fau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtum li. xxij. ca. xxxv.</note> or of bothe ſides. &amp; if yt were leful &amp; not agaynſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law of nature than for men to mary their ſiſters: it is not againſt the law of nature then for a man to mary his brothers &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">ſuper mat. ho m. xlix</note>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Oly Criſoſtome doth ſhewe reaſonable cauſes why almighty God did comma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>und the Iues to mary their brothers wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows &amp;c. a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d than ſuche mariage cannot be againſt the law of nature and reaſon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Ertulian / theis deceyuers doctoure d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oith allege certayne cauſes which be iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ged good and reaſonable why the iues ſhulde in the tyme of the olde law ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rey their brothers wiues widows &amp;c. Wherfor he did not iuge ſuche mariage to be againſt the lawe of reaſon: ſeinge he aſſigned (after his mynde) reaſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nable cauſes: wherby men might lefully mary th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eir brothers widows. yet ye ſhall vnderſtonde th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at I doo not approue Tertulians reaſons / that he ſhewith for ſuche mariage: but yet by his reaſons it appereth that he did not iuge mariage betwene the brother and the brothers widow &amp;c. to be agai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nſt the lawe of reaſon and nature.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Vperte vpon the leuitical / ſaith that Abr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aham after the cuſtome of the heithens / a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
<pb facs="tcp:11164:51"/> the which he dwellyd / did marey his owne ſiſter: and yet for all that he did not ſyn / for aſmoc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>he as vnto that tyme / he had not by the law com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement to the contrary: nor yet by the voice of almyghty god. Now where ther is no commau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ndment (ſaith he) there is no tranſgreſſion of the law. ſo by this doctours ſaynge / ye may clerely ſe / that it is not againſt the law of nature for a man to mary his ſiſter / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d than it is not againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law of nature for a man to marcy his brothers wife le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ft without yſſewe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ewgh of ſaynte victore ſaith that in the inſtitution of matrimony / there were but two perſons excepte:<note place="margin">li. iij. de ſacram<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ento p. ij. ca. iiij</note> that is but the fath<hi rend="sup">r</hi> and the mother: ſo that it was forbiden than / that the father ſhulde not mary with the doughter / n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or the mother with the ſonne. but al other perſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es might lefully mary togither by the firſt inſtit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ucion of matrimony. After this (ſaith this docto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ur) came the ſeconde inſtitution of matrimony / w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hich was made by the lawe writen / and that did e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xcepte certayne other perſones beſyde the father and the mother / and this was done / other for to ornate nature / or els to augment and encreaſe ch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtite. And than to marey the Brother wythe the Siſter or the nere kynſman withe the nere kynſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman began to be vnlefull by the prohibicion th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at before was lefull / and graunted by nature.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:11164:52"/>
               <p>By this doctours mynde ye may euidently ſe / th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at it is not againſt the law of nature for a man to mary his ſiſter / and than it folowith that it is not againſt the lawe of nature / for a man to mary his brothers wife a widowe &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">ix. lib. iiij. art. xiij.</note>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ainte Thomas ſaith that the prohibicion leuitical that forbideth that a man may n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ot mary his ſiſter / ys a prohibicion and a c<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ommaundment iudiciall / and he in likewiſe ſaith in another place / <note place="margin">p<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. ij. 2. q. 9. ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti. iiij.</note> that it was not forbiden bi y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law of nature that a man ſhulde not marey his ſiſter / wherfore yf it be not againſt the law of nature for a man to marey his ſiſter / it is not againſt the law of nature for a man to marey his brothers wife a widowe left &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">In .iiij. ſen. diſ. xl. cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>por. q<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt.</note>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Aynte Thomas agayne ſaith that by the lawe of nature / it is forbiden that the fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>her ſhal not marey his doughter nor y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hir ſonne: other perſones nere of kyn be forbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den / bi the lawe of God / and than it folowith that for a man to marey his brothers widowe &amp;c. is not againſt the law of nature.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Eter of Bleſen ſaith that at the beginnin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge there were no mo perſons excepte from matrimony / but the father and mother / &amp; is to ſaye: that the father may not mary the doug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hter / nor y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mother with the ſone. And therfor ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th
<pb facs="tcp:11164:52"/> this doctour / it was ſayd for matrimony / a man ſhal leaue and forſake his father and his mother / and take him to his wife. But afterwarde (ſaith he) the lawmaker did excepte mo perſons and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bade mo degres.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ainte Bonauenture in anſweringe to an argument that infideles whiche tourne to criſtes faith ought not to retayne their wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues whiche they had maried before / <note place="margin">In .iiij. diſtinct. xxxix. q<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt. iiij.</note> yf ſo be they had maryed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelf to their ſiſters / or nere kinſw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>omen / ſuche as be againſt the ordre that Chriſten people do kepe in mariage / ſaith thus: that for a man to mary his ſiſter is forbiden bi the commau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ndment of the churche: and therfore when heithen turne to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faith they muſt conforme the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelf after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ordre of the chirch: &amp; not to mary againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> churches prohibicion: but if thei maried their ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters befor: than thei may not be ſeparate: for the or<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dinaunce of the churche doith not extende to that / ſo ſaynte bonauenture doith ſaye that for a man to mary his ſiſter / is but againſt the law of the chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che / and not againſt the law of nature: for yf it we<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re againſt the law of nature: than the ordinaunce of the church wolde diſſolue and breke it: the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ſaynte Bonauenture ſaith / the church can not do: and than / yf it be not agaynſt the law of natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re for a man to mary his ſiſter / it is not againſt the law of nature for a man to mary his brothers w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>idowe &amp;cete.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:11164:53"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">In .iiij. diſt. xl. concluſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>one ij.</note>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Homas alſo of Argentyne ſhewe that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelis maye marey in the degreis that be forbiden to Criſten men. For if they be I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues / than thei may mary with their kinſwomen in the .iii. and .iiij. degre: for ther was forbidden to them but the firſte and ſeconde degre as ſhew the xviij. Chapiter of the leuitical / and yf the infide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les be gentils and folowe onely the law of nature than they may mary in the firſt and ſecond degre: for thowgh the writen law poſitiue / do forbid ſuch mariages: yet it ſemith that the law of nature do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ith not forbid them: the which is manifeſt in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de fathers that were before the law. For abraham maried his ſiſter / and Iacob his vncles doughter. and if yt be not againſte the lawe of nature / for a a man to mary his ſiſter: it is not againſte the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we of nature for a man to mary his brothers wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owe left without yſſew.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lſo Pope zachary ſaith (which theſe deceiuers do allege for them in their boke) that it is more forbide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that a m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an ſhal not mary his fathers goddo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ughter: and that a man ought more forbeer to marey with hir / than to marey with his fathers doughter: &amp; yet it is euident / that it ys not againſt the law of God nor againſt the law of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture for a man to marey his fathers goddoughter for that is forbiden but onely by the lawe of the c<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hurche. Wherfore it folowith that it is not agay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nſt
<pb facs="tcp:11164:53"/> the law of nature for a man to mary his fath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers dowghter. For yf that thinge that is more for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biden be not againſt the law of nature: than that thinge that is leſſe forbidden in the ſame kynde of forbidinge / ys not agaynſt the law of nature / and this pope Zakary ſpeaketh of one maner of forbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ddinge of mariage / and than yt folowith vpon th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is ſaynge of this Pope that it ys not againſte the lawe of nature for a man to mary his ſiſter. And ſo than it is not againſt the law of nature for a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to marey his brothers widowe &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow ye haue harde by theis holy fath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and men of greate lernynge how y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it ys not againſte the lawe of nature / for a man to mary his ſiſter. Wherof folowith that it is not agaynſte the l<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awe of nature for a man to mary his brothers wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe a widowe left withe owte yſſewe. The hole vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuerſal numbre of expownders of holy Scripture doo affyrme / that frome the firſte Inſtitucion of matrimony vnto the tyme of the lawe of Moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: there were no moo perſones excepte and forbidden to marey to gether by the lawe of n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ature: but theſe / The Father wythe the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wghter / and the Mother withe the Sone / All other perſones myght marey to gether in the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de lyne yn eny maner of degre of conſanguini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te or affynite.<note place="margin">co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. fan. li. xxij. ca. xlvij</note> Wherfore Saynte Auguſtyn d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>othe defend the holy Patriarke Iacobe the whiche
<pb facs="tcp:11164:54"/> maried two ſiſters and hade them bothe at ons: a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d they were his nere kynſwoman / for in the ſeconde degre / and the one of them was ioyned to hym by Alians in the firſt degre of affinite / and beſyde th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eis two wiues / this holy man Iacob had oth<hi rend="sup">r</hi> two wiues and thei were to him and amonge them ſelf in the ſame degre of affinite. And yet ſaynte Aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſtyn doth iuſtify this holy patriarke Iacob in th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us marying: ſayng on this wiſe. yt is ſaid on to I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acob for a greate offence that he had fower wyves but he is cleryd and quite of this offence by a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall proclamacion. Firſt for aſmoche / as when the maner and cuſtome was to haue moo wiues than one / than to mary ſo was non offence. but to haue moo wyues at ons nowe / ys offence: by cauſe that the cuſtome is contrary / and it folowith anone af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Sum ſynnes and offenſis be againſt nature. Sum be agaynſt cuſtoms / and ſum be againſt p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>receptis and commaundmentis / and whan it ys t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hus / what offence is laid to this holy man Iacobe in hauinge many wyues? &amp; yf ye aſke nature why Iacob had ſo many wyues / ſhe wil anſwere for h<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ym that he dide not take them fore the inordin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate luſte and pleaſure of the bodye: but he vſid his wiues to encreaſe and multiply faithful people / if yow aſke cuſtome why Iacobe toke ſo many wiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es: it will anſwere that at that tyme in that coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try their maner was ſo to mary: if ye aſke the com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maundement why Iacobe toke ſo many wiues: it he wil anſwere / for bi cauſe that ther was no law
<pb facs="tcp:11164:54"/> that forbode yt. but wherfore ys it nowe an offence to take mo wyues at ons than one? that is for bec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>auſe lawes and cuſtomes do forbyd it / ye and that althoughe a man wolde take moo wiues for to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe and multyply faithful people. Thus yowe maye ſe by ſaynte Auſtyn that it is not agaynſte the lawe of nature for a man to mary in the firſte degre of affinite. Parauenture ſum wil make this obieccion / and ſaye that almyghty God did diſpen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce with Iacob that he myght mary on the reherſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>id wiſe / and in ſuche degreis of affinite and conſan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>guinite / and ſo he did likewiſe with other holy m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en before the law. ſaynte Auguſtyns wordes do ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke this obieccion clene awaye: for a diſpenſacion (to this purpoſe here) is a lycence graunted againſte ſum lawe or a declaracion of ſum lawe. And by ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynte Auſtyns wordes than ther was no lawe th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at forbode Iacob ſo to mary / and than had he no nede of licence to mary ſo: nor there was no law to be declared / and therfore after ſaynte Auguſtines mynde: Iacobe did not offende againſt the lawe of nature / and than after this tyme almyghty God did forbide certayne degreis of conſanguinite and affinite: as the firſt and ſecond by law poſitiue and commaundement which Moyſes did declare vnto the people: and theſe prohibicions haue now no ſtr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ength / but by a newe ordinaunce which that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urche made that Criſten people ſhulde not nowe mary in theis degres nor in the thirde. Thus ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue ye harde before of the ſentence of Thomas of
<pb facs="tcp:11164:55"/> Argentyne / and the prohibicion leuital: that a m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an ſhulde not mary his brothers wife (vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de a widow) to be a law poſitiue: and the ſame we may haue of holy Chriſoſtoms ſayng.<note place="margin">ſuper matth. ho. xlix</note> He ſhewi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th why almyghty God commaundid the Iues to mary their brothers wifis widowes left without yſſewe. And than he aſked whi a man myght not mary his brothers widowe that had children left by hir huſbonde. To this he anſwerethe and ſaye that it was done for by cawſe that the lawe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker wolde haue affinite to go further a brode / wh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erby men myght be knyt togither. So by thys yt apereth that the prohibicion leuiticall whiche for bode that a man ſhulde not mary his brothers w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>idow / was a lawe poſitiue and a politicall precep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te which nowe hathe no ſtrengthe but bi the reaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the conſtitucion of the church. Alſo it do ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ere that it ys not agaynſte the law of nature for a man to mary his ſiſter: his nere kinſwomen: for yf the cuſtome &amp; law of the churche to the contrarye were a waye / many diſcrete men with right iuge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of reaſon had leuer mary their ſiſter and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re kinſwomen than other women. And yet not for no filthye nor vnclenly deſire: but rather for the na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tural loue that thei haue to their kinſwomen / th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ey ſhuld be moued to vſe them verey honeſtly yn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>al actis: ye &amp; myche better than thei ſhuld vſe eny other women. This I ſuppoſe that the moſt par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te of diſcrete men &amp; women (y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> do or wil examyn t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>his wel) wil thꝰ iuge. Thus now ye may perceyue
<pb facs="tcp:11164:55"/> that it is not againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law of nature for a man to marey his brothers wife a widow left without &amp;c</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow I ſhal ſhew ye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is not againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law of God for a man to mary hys brothers wife a widow &amp;c. Firſt it ys not agaynſt the olde law of God: but there ys and was a commaunded law vniuerſall / &amp; bounde al the Iues to mary always their brothers wiues left &amp;c. and that vpon a gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at payne as ye haue herd declared before / and no man can ſaye that the Iues maried their brothers wiues widowes &amp;c. by a licence &amp; diſpenſacion of al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mighty God: for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye haue ſeyn manifeſtly impr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouid.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Aynte Chriſoſtome ſaith that the law did compel the iues to mary their brothers w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ifes widows &amp;ce. &amp; ſo ſuche mariage is not agaynſt the olde lawe / but it was ther co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundid<note place="margin">ſuper Mat. ca. xxii ho. lxxi</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lſo for a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to mary his broth<hi rend="sup">r</hi>s widowe &amp;c. is not againſt criſtes law: but rath<hi rend="sup">r</hi> o<hi rend="sup">r</hi> ſauio<hi rend="sup">r</hi> criſt did approue ſuche mariage as ye ſaw he<hi rend="sup">r</hi> at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beginning of myn anſwe<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. alſo in alt he newe Teſtament there is no expreſſid prohibicion aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deutronomical precepte which bonde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iues to mary their broth<hi rend="sup">r</hi>s wiues widowes &amp;c. nor yet of al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> newe teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can gath<hi rend="sup">r</hi> to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude a prohibicion againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuteronomicall commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dment / ye &amp; beſide this ther is no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude
<pb facs="tcp:11164:56"/> of eny ſcripture in the newe Teſtament eny prohibicion to let Mariage in eny degre of affinite or conſanguinite beſide the prohibicion of the lawe of nature / this is manifeſt: wherfore / for a man to mary his brothers wife a widowe is not againſte the law of God / for it is nether againſte the newe lawe nor the olde.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Vt yet for aſmuche as diuers Docto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urs do ſaye / that it is againſt the law of God to mary in the firſt and ſecond degre of conſanguinite and of affinite ye ſhal vnderſtande that the churche hath made certayne conſtitucions and lawes vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the iudiciall commaundments and examples of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> olde lawe / as that prieſtes and religions men ſhal ſaye their Canonical howres and ſeruice / of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ich conſtitucion the church toke their grounde in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> olde law: as in the Pſalme Septies in die laudem dixi tibi domine. And agayne / media nocte ſurge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bam ad confitendum tibi. Likewiſe the church ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th ordined and conſtitute that we ſhal faſte the le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nte: In the making of this law / the churche grou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nded it in the examples of the holy fathers of the olde lawe: which faſted .xl. dayes: and in the exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mple of the faſtinge of our ſauiour Chriſt / and v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon this ſaynte Auguſtine / ſaynte Hierome / &amp; m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aximyn / ſaye that the lent is commaundid to be kept and faſted vi the law of God. Alſo the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che hath ordined and decreid that no man ſhal m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary
<pb facs="tcp:11164:56"/> in the firſt and ſecond degre of affinite and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nſanguinite / and toke example and occaſion in the prohibicions of the olde lawe in makyng this decre and ordinaunce / and therfor often tymes doctours ſaye that it is forbiden by the lawe of God that a man ſhal not mary in theis degreis. Wherfor the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe reherſid thinges and lawes which be only ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunces of the church / yet be thei callid the lawes of God: for becauſe the church in makinge them to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke occaſion and example in the olde law / Therfor when eny doctour ſaith yt ys forbiden by the lawe of God / that a man may not mary in the firſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gre of conſanguinite and affinite: yt muſt be vnd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erſtande that ſuche mariage is ſayd to be forbiden by the lawe of God: bycauſe that vppon the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibicions in the olde lawe (which now haue ſtren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gth) the church hath made a newe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtitucion w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hich doith forbid mariage in theis degreis. This rwle perceyued / now I will ſhew that the Pope h<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ath power to diſpence and licence a man to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry his brothers wife a widowe left &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Pope haith power to licence &amp; diſpence againſt eny prohibicion made bi the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ch: This is ſo euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no man can deny yt And it is onely a prohibicion of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a man ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hal not mary his brothers wife a widow &amp;c. Wh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfor yt folowith that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pope may in this caſe lice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nce &amp; diſpence / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a man may mary his brothers wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe a widowe left &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:11164:57"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His reaſon and argument is good / and the firſt propoſicion of it is trew. And the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor and ſeconde propoſicion I wil proue / t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hat it is but onely a prohibicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may not mary his brothers widowe &amp;c. Firſt it is not forbiden bi y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law of nature / nor bi the olde law nor in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> newe law / as ye haue hard. Wherfor ſuch mariage is only forbiden by the prohibicion of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> c<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hurche.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">in .iiij diſt. yf.</note>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ſame doith affirme Maſter dunſe / ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ng y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> affinite ſettith matrimony. but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is not but bicauſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtatute of the church. &amp; ſo than it is not forbide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / but by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtatute of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che that a man ſhall not mary his brothers wife a widowe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">in .iiij diſt. xl. q<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt. ij. in corpo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re queſt</note>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Aynte Bonauenture ſaith y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is not vnle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful for a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to mary his ſiſt<hi rend="sup">r</hi> / but for bicau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe that the ſtatute of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church hath forbide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no man ſhal mary his ſiſt<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. &amp; tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it folowith y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is not forbide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / but by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtatute of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal mary his brothers widowe &amp;ce. for this can be no more forbiden than the tothere.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">in. iiii. diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>nc. xxxix. q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>in.</note>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lſo ſaynte Bonauenture ſaith y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a Iue w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hich hath maryed his brothers wife a w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>idowe / &amp; ſo turneth to criſten faith: ought not to be diuorced from his wife. &amp; ſo by this holy Bonauenturs ſayng / it is not forbiden but by the church that a man ſhal not mary his brothers w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ife a widowe. For yf ſuche mariage were forbiden / 
<pb facs="tcp:11164:57"/> other by the law of God / or by the lawe of nature than the iewe that had ſo maried &amp; cam to the fait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>he: ought to be diuorced &amp; ſeperat from his wife: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which Bonauenture doith deny / wherfor it is not forbiden / but by the ordinaunce of the churche y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a man ſhal not mary his brothere widowe &amp;c.</p>
               <p>ALſo theis falſe deceiuers great doctour Pet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er de Palude expoundinge the .xviij. chapi. leuitical / ſaith y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all degreis of affinite theyr conteyned ſemed to be forbiden by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law poſitiue.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lſo Frances Marro ſaith y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beginninge of criſtes churche / affinite did not let perſons to mary togith<hi rend="sup">r</hi>:<note place="margin">In .iiij diſt. xli q<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtio. v nica In ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plemeit to gavi elis in iiij. diſt. xli. q. i.</note> for ther was than no law po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſitiue for it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Endelyn ſaith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> affinite lettith mariage o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nely by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtatute of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church: whiche haue ordined y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> perſons ioyned in certayne degre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is of affinite / ſhal not mary togither.</p>
               <p>¶ Now by theis doctours myndis / ye may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceue / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is onely forbiden by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law of the churche y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a man may not mary his brothers widow. wh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfor the minor / &amp; ſeconde propoſicion of the reaſon principal is trewe. &amp; ſo is this concluſion / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pope may licence and diſpence y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may mary his b<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rothers wif a widow &amp;c. Ther be alſo doctours t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hat do confirme this concluſion. Firſt Peter de Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lude expounding y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .xviij. cha. leuitical ſaith that it ſemith that the pope maye diſpence in al degreis of affinite that be conteyned in the ſame chapiter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:11164:58"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">In .iiij. diſt. xli q<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſti. iij.</note>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>lſo doctour De rubone ſaith y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church may diſpence in any maner of degre of affinite or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſanguinite y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſide lyne: as with the bro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>th<hi rend="sup">r</hi> &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſiſter / &amp; ſo furth in conſanguinite / &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> broth<hi rend="sup">r</hi> with the brothers widow &amp; ſo furth in affinite.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">ſuper decre. xxxv. q<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt. ij. iij</note>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lſo Iohn Cardinal de Turre Cremata diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>putinge in the degreis of affinite &amp; conſang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinite &amp; aft<hi rend="sup">r</hi> anſweringe to an obiection that he maide againſt this. That the Pope ſuffereth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iues that hade maryed their brothers wiues acc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinge to the olde lawe to retayne their wiues ſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ill after y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they be Criſtened. He ſaith yf a man died without yſſew / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> than yt was not forbide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law of God / but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the broth<hi rend="sup">r</hi> might mary the brothers wife / &amp; therfor he ſaith y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Pope doith not prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erly diſpence with the Iues y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thus come to that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ith. But rath<hi rend="sup">r</hi> he doith commaund or conſent that the Iues: ſhal ſtil remayne with their brothers w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>idows that thei haue maryed / ſo by this doctours mynde it was not forbiden in the olde law y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a man might not mary his brothers widowe left witho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ut &amp;c. alſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Pope may co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent to ſuch mariage<note place="margin">In com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>menta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>undam ſecunde diui thome.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lſo Tacitan ſaith y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pope may diſpence with al ꝑſons in mariage exc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dought<hi rend="sup">r</hi> / &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſone with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moth<hi rend="sup">r</hi>: n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ow bi thies doctours myndis ye ſe that the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> principal argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is trew / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pope maye diſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may mary his broth<hi rend="sup">r</hi>s widowe &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:11164:58"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>ow beſide al this euident profe: yet to ſta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bleſſhe and fortify this vndowtid trowth that a man may by the Popes licence m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary his brothers widow &amp;c. I wil ſhew ye the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me truth by experiens of Popes which haue diſp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enſyd in lyke mariage / or in mariage y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is as great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly forbide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as for a man to mary his brothers wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ow &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt Pope Innocent the thirde / willed and conſentid that Liuonienſes which had maryed their brothers wiues / and afterwarde turned and came to Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes fayth / that they ſhuld continewe and kepe ſtil their brothers widows / as it apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth yn the decretallis / capi. deus qui eccleſiam.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lſo Pope Martin the fiueth did diſp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and licence that the brother whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ch had knowen his own ſiſter carnal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly / to mary afterwarde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame ſiſter</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Nd Pope Alexandre the ſixte did li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence the kinge of Portingale that faſt was / to mary his wiues ſiſter / not withſtanding that he had by his firſt wife a childe. And alſo the ſame Pope diſpenſed with the ſame kinge after the dethe of his ſeconde wife / his firſt wiues ſiſter to mary his wiues ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e: and yet he had ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny children by the ſecond wife.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:11164:59"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lſo Pope Alexandre did licenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; diſpence w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ith Don ferdinando king of Cycill to marey his fathers ſiſter: which is more than to diſp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence with a man to marey his brothers widow &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>ANd Pope Iuly the ſecond did diſpence withe the king of Englonde that he myght marey his brothers wife a widowe left &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Nd Pope Leo the tenth grauntid vnto the Auſtyn fryers thorowgh Criſten<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome that they myght diſpence in the firſt degre of affinite: that is to ſay th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at yf the brother had maryed or contr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acte with the brothers widow wittingly or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe: that thois fryers might licence thois perſons to continewe ſtill ſo maryed: ſo that the perſones maryed or contracte in that degre of affinite were not accuſed / nor openly complayned on befor a iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge or ere they required the diſpenſacion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lſo in lyke degre of affinite the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe did diſpence nowe of late withe a noble man of France / who is called my Lorde of luce: ſo thus now yowe maye ſe by the Doctours myndes / and bi the experience of the Popes e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xcerciſinge in this caſe licens and diſpenſacion / that the Pope maye licence a man to mary his br<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>others widowe &amp; ceter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:11164:59"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Inally / this confirmith the greate ler<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyd co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel of Princes &amp; Kingis: whiche were examined to ſhew y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> treuth / wh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth<hi rend="sup">r</hi> that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pope had power to licence men to marey in the afore reherſide d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>egreis of affinite &amp; conſanguinite / And theis great lerned men y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were of thoſe kingis &amp; princes counſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſailles affirmed &amp; graunted / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Pope myght li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence &amp; diſpence vpon ſuche mariage / &amp; ſo did alſo the popes lernyd counſayl / ye &amp; ſo dide the vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal noumbre of the lernyd men in Criſtendome: for thei herde &amp; knew of ſuche licences &amp; diſpenſacions graunted. And the mariages bi the licences were made / and yet they neuer reclamyd nor ſpoke ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ainſt them. Wherfore now ye may euidentli ſe and perceue / that the opinion of theſe deceyuers is fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe: where as they ſay that it is againſt the lawe of God / &amp; againſt the law of nature: for a man to m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary his brothers widowe &amp;cet. And that the Pope hath no power to diſpence vpon ſuche mariage / &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this is verey trew / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> for a man to mary his brot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hers wife a widowe / is nother againſt the law of God / nor againſte the lawe of nature: and that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pope hath power to diſpence vppon ſuche maria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge. And alſo by this / yowe maye clerely ſee / that the determinacions of the vniuerſytes / be man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yfeſtly falſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow theſe deceyuers opinion thus openly reprouide / and ſhewid to be falſe / and the
<pb facs="tcp:11164:60"/> trewth in this matter declared: I wil retourne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne vnto their boke.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>n the .lxxxxiiij. leif of their boke theis perſons ſaye that there be many / and that ſtronge and inuincible reſons / the which may ſeme to declare &amp; lyghten the ſentence of thuniuerſites / &amp; theys reaſons thei wil bring in. &amp; for this purpoſe thei b<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in many diffinicions and deſcriptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law of God / &amp; of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law of nature &amp;c. The which I doo not paſſe vpon: bycauſe I wolde not be to longe / &amp; ſo I come to the .c. viij. leif of their boke / where as they ſay on this wiſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Herfore ſeyng that God him ſelf here doi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th playnly pronounce &amp; giue ſentence: that the Cananeis and Egipcians did file th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eir lande and ſpot yt with filthynes / while that t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hey did contracte mariage with their brothers w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ifes: &amp; that he / for that cauſe did greatly aborre th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>em: &amp; did moſt rightfully take vengeaunce vppon them &amp; punyſhed them moſt ſharply: yt cannot be no nother wiſe / but it muſt nedis folowe / that god hath iuged this thinge to be ſhamfully vnhoneſt: &amp; of it ſelf (as they ſay) morally evill &amp; nowght: a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d alſo againſte the rightwiſnes of natural law &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſon: ye &amp; to be abhominable &amp; abhorred. This is theſe falſe deceyuers owne ſaynge / &amp; note &amp; merke it wel. Firſt it is manifeſtly falſe / for almyghty g<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>od
<pb facs="tcp:11164:60"/> did neuer punyſhe the Egipcians &amp; Cananeis for becauſe they maryed their brothers wiues wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes left &amp;c. Nor he did neuer abhorre them / nor ther is no ſcripture / nor doctour y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaith that almy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghty God did deſtroye / &amp; punyſhe the Cananeis &amp; Egiptians / becauſe thei maried their brothers widows. Wherfor it is ſhamfully falſe: to ſay y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mighty God did punyſhe &amp; deſtroy the Cananeis &amp; the Egipcia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s for marying their brothers wiues widowes left &amp;ce.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lſo in this their ſayng / theſe deceyu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers ſpeke directly againſt their owne writinge / for in the .lvj. leif of their v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oke they write / that the verey heyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens after the deth of their wiues did euermore abſtayne fro mariyng of their wiues ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters as from a certayne impietie or abhominacion ageynſt nature. This thei wrote there / &amp; here th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ey write y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> almighty God did take vengeaunce v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the Cananeis &amp; Egipcians for marying of t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heir brothers widows &amp;c. the whiche is nomore im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pietie than for a man to mary his wyues ſiſter af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their owne opinion: yet beſide this / theſe dece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yuers in their a fore reherſid ſaynge do greatly diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>piſe and hiely blaſpheme almighty God / for it fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowithe of this their ſaynge that almyghty God in commaundinge the iues to mary their brothers wiues widowes lefte &amp;c. that he commaundid the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to fyle &amp; ſpotte their lande with filthines / while y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11164:61"/> they did contracte mariage with their brothers w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>idows &amp;c. &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> for fulfillinge of his commaundme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t he did abhorre the Iues / ye &amp; of theſe deceyuers ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ayng / it folowith that almighty God in comma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unding them to mary their brothers wiues wido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ws / did commaunde them to do that thinge: for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which he ſhulde take right vengeaunce vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; punyſhe them moſt ſherpely / &amp; alſo that almig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hty God did commaunde the Iues to do y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thinge / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which ys ſhamfully vnhoneſt / &amp; of it ſelf mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally euill / &amp; nowght / &amp; againſt the rightwiſnes of naturall lawe and reaſon / ye &amp; to be abhominable &amp; abhorred. Al this theſe perſons ſaye by maria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge betwene the brother &amp; the brothers widowe &amp;c. For of this maner of mariage / is their ſpekinge: or els it is not for their purpoſe / &amp; almighty God co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mmaundide the Iues to mary their Brothers w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>idowes left &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Nd this did not almyghty God onely co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde: but alſo commaundid to punyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>he with a greuous payne al theſe that w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olde not mary their brothers widows / wherfore to diſpiſe ſuche mariage / is nothing els / but to diſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe &amp; blaſpheme almyghty God: which commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſuche mariage. Who euer herde eny man that durſt ſaye that almyghty God did commaunde e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny maner of people to do that thing / which is ſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amfully vnhoneſt of it ſelf / &amp; morally euil &amp;c. as t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heſe blaſphemers ſaye mariage to be betwene the
<pb facs="tcp:11164:61"/> brother and the brothers widowe lefte witheowte yſſew / ys? Whiche Almyghty God did comma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unde. Therfore yowe maye clerly ſe how hiely &amp; greuouſly theſe perſones blaſpheme almightye God. Here now yowe haue herde one of theſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſones inuincible reaſons / that they ſayd they wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de bringe in for to gyue light vnto the determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions of their vniuerſites.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the .c. and .xj. leif of their boke theſe perſones ſaye that ther was neuer n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acion ſo beiſtly / none ſo withoute al h<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umanite / but that they perceyued and knew / that thei ought this honour d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ewtye / and reuerence to their brothern / &amp; brothers wiues: that they ſhuld refrayne from their mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages. This is theſe perſons owne ſayng: here thei diſpiſe &amp; blaſpheme almyghty God agayne: for of this their ſayng / it folowith that almyghty God in commaundinge the Iues to mary their brothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rs wiues / that he was more beſt lier than eny nac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion / and that he did not perceiue / nor knew that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people oughte this honore / dewtie / and reuerence vnto their brothern / and brothers wiues: that thei ſhuld refrayne frome their mariages. This great blaſphemy yow maye ſe folowith of their ſaynge. And thus nowe yowe haue herde a nother of t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heis perſons inuincible reaſons. In the ſame leif of their boke / theis perſones ſaye / that he that haith ſene eny thynge yn the olde ſtories and l<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awes
<pb facs="tcp:11164:62"/> muſt nedis know that this maner of inceſte haue bene hadde in great infamy / reproue / &amp; ſclau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ndre / &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> not onely in one cite / or contrey: but alm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſt in euery place / &amp; emong al men bene condempn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as a certayne wikednes againſt nature. This is agaynſt theſe perſons owne ſayng: wheryn thei adde more blaſphemy. For of this ſayng it folow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that almyghty God in commaunding the iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es to mary their brothers widows &amp;c. commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did them / &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vpon a great payne / to do y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thinge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is condempned in al contreis &amp; cities / for a certay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne wikednes againſt nature. Here now ye haue h<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erde another of their reaſons inuincible: Sewrely theſe may wel be called ſtronge &amp; inuincible reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ns / in blaſpheming &amp; diſpiſinge of almygty God for I thinke no man / no nor yet the deuyl him ſelf can make none ſtronger / nor more inuincible for to diſpiſe &amp; blaſpheme almyghty God than theſe pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtilent perſones do here make.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Vt now for aſmuche as theſe vngrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ious perſones do thus diſpiſe &amp; blaſp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heme / not onely almyghty God: but alſo his holy lawe &amp; commaundment I am compellid to deſire ye to cal to y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owr remembraunce that thing which I haue ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wid ye before / that ys to ſaye / that almighty God did neuer in al the olde lawe commaunde eny thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nge to be continually kepte / &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vpon a payne: but that which was iuſte / goode / &amp; holy / &amp; a meane th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at
<pb facs="tcp:11164:62"/> the kepers of it might beſauide / &amp; come to euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtinge life. And therfore almighty God ſayth Cuſtodite leges meas atque iudicia:<note place="margin">leuiti. xviij</note> que facie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mo / viuet in eis. And this ys the cauſe that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bliſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Apoſtle callith the olde lawe holy / &amp; the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundment holy / iuſte &amp; gud / ſayng.<note place="margin">ro. vij.</note> Lex quidem ſancta / &amp; mandatum ſanctum / iuſtum / &amp; bonum. For thowghe the Iues in the olde lawe vſed cert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ayne thinges that were neth<hi rend="sup">r</hi> good nor godly / yet was ther nothing commaundid in the olde law to be continually kepte / but that was holy iuſte &amp; g<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ood to the keper: &amp; (as I haue ſayd) a meane / whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rby he might be iuſtified &amp; ſauid / &amp; in that lawe it was commaundid that euery man ſhulde alwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ys mary their brothers widow &amp;c. wherfore ſuche mariage was holy / iuſte / &amp; gud. This Argument is euident / both by the very wordes of almyghty God / and alſo by the wordes of the Apoſtle / &amp; ſo now by this ye may euidently perceyue howe that theſe vngracious perſones / in diſpiſinge of maria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge betwene the brother &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> brothers widowe &amp;c. do diſpiſe &amp; blaſpheme almighty God &amp; his holy law</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the .c. vij. leife of their boke they ſay that they wil ſhew two reaſons / whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ch ſhal proue as ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly as it can be / th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at a man can not mary his brothers wife. Firſt bicauſe that affinite doith aſwell lete mariage as doith conſanguinite. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde / becauſe that he that ſo marieth dothe ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me
<pb facs="tcp:11164:63"/> &amp; diſhoneſtye vnto his father. And for to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue the firſt reaſon / theſe perſones ſaye / that not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nely by the lawe of God ſo many perſons be excl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>udid from mariage in the lyne of affinite / as to be excludid and forbide in the lyne of conſanguinite: but that alſo the church is compellid to ſet the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ndes of mariage in the lynes / bothe of affinite and conſanguinite in like diſtance and degre / and for to ſhewe this ordinaunce of the churche / theis perſons bringe in ſaynte Gregore / and Pope Iuly / ſaynte Auſten / Iſodore / &amp; maiſter Abbot. Thus nowe I ſuppoſe theſe perſones wold make their argument Affinite doith as wel let mariage as conſauguini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te: but it is forbiden by the lawe of God / &amp; bi the l<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aw of nature that a man ſhal not mary his ſiſter / bicauſe of their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſanguinite: Wherfor it is forbide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bi the law of god &amp; bi y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law of nature: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a man ſhal not mary his broth<hi rend="sup">r</hi>s wife becauſe of their affinite To this argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t I wil anſwer. Firſt with theyr own doctours ſaynge Peter de Palude which exp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ounding y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .xviij. chap. leuitical / ſaith y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it femeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pope may diſpence in al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> degreis of affinite ther conteyned / but not in all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> degreis of conſanguini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te / &amp; with this ſayng / this doctour doith deny the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe perſons principal propoſicion of their argument which is this: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> affinite doith as well let mariage as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſanguinite / for he ſaith y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> affinite doith not let mariage as doith co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſanguinite / bicauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> (after his mynde) y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pope may diſpence in al degreis of affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teyned in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .xviij. chap. of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leuitical law: &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:11164:63"/> ſo he can not in al degreis of conſanguinite that be there forbiden.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lſo this firſt &amp; principal propoſition of theſe perſons argument is falſe: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> affinite doith aſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wel let mariage as conſanguinite: for conſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nguinite may let mariage by the law of nature / as the father may not mary with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dowght<hi rend="sup">r</hi> / nor the ſone with the moth<hi rend="sup">r</hi> / by reaſon of their conſangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite: &amp; therfor theſe perſons were forbiden to mary togither bi the law of nature / &amp; exempte at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſte inſtitucion of matrimony / but ſo we<hi rend="sup">r</hi> no man<hi rend="sup">r</hi> of ꝑ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in no degre of affinite: wherfo<hi rend="sup">r</hi> this propoſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is falſe / that affinite doith as well let mariage as doith conſanguinite.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lſo in the decreys Ca. Non dz / extra de con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanguinitate &amp; affinitate / yt is writen &amp; dec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rreyd that the childe that is had in the ſecon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de mariage may mary with the kynne of the firſte huſbonde / &amp; thꝰ if I maried a wife &amp; ſo died / the ch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ildren y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> my wife had by a noth<hi rend="sup">r</hi> man / might mary with my kinne / as the ſone y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> my wife had bi a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man / might mary my ſiſter / notwithſtandin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge the affinite that was ſumtyme betwene my ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter &amp; my wife: &amp; this decre was made by counſail general / but after my dethe my ſone may not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry with my ſiſter / by the reaſon of conſanguinite / which by me remayneth ſtil in my ſone toward mi ſiſter. And therfore it is ſalſe to ſaye that affinyte doith aſwel let mariage as doith conſanguinite.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:11164:64"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irthermore &amp; yf it were grauntid th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at affinite which is betwene the brot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>her &amp; the brothers widowe did as well let mariage as doith conſanguinite th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at is betwene the brother &amp; the ſiſter: yet this grauntid / it wolde nothinge helpe theis d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eceyuers falſe opinion / for it is nether againſte the law of God / nor agaynſt the lawe of nature for a man to mary his ſiſter. Firſt it is not againſte the law of nature for a man to mary his ſiſter / as ye haue harde it declaryd before: nor it is not agaynſt Criſtes law. For owr ſauiour Criſt did neuer for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide ſuche mariage: nor no man can co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude of eny ſcripture in al the newe teſtament / that it ſhulde be forbiden that a man may not mary his ſiſter: &amp; as to the olde lawe where it was forbidden that a man ſhuld not mary his ſiſter: that prohibicion n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owe hath no ſtrengthe: &amp; therfor yt ys not forbide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bi the law of God nor by the law of nature for a man to mary his ſiſter. Wherfore the ſeconde pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſicion of theſe perſons Argument is alſo falſe: whiche is this. That it is againſt the law of God &amp; againſt the law of nature / for a man to mary his ſiſter. &amp; therfore their concluſion is falſe / which is this / that it is againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law of God &amp; againſt the lawe of nature / for a man to marry his brothers wife a widowe left without yſſewe. Thus yowe maye ſee that theis deceyuers firſt reaſon in falſe and nowghte.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:11164:64"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ſeconde reaſon / that theis perſons ſay doith openly proue that a man can not m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary his brother wife a widow &amp;c. is thys. bycauſe that he that ſo maryeth doith ſhame &amp; diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>honeſtye to his father. The which in the .cxxviij leif of their boke they go abowte to declare on this wiſe: He that maryeth his brothers wife / takithe his fathers fleſſhe &amp; blode to mariage: the whiche thing playnly is againſt the lawe of nature / for ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eynge the huſbonde &amp; the wife be one fleſſhe &amp; blo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de: truly he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> takith his brothers wife / takith alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſſhe &amp; blode of his fath<hi rend="sup">r</hi> / &amp; as for our broth<hi rend="sup">r</hi> is the fleſſhe &amp; blode of our father &amp; mother / &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more nerer to them than eny of bothe their ſiſters / bec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>auſe he is their owne ſone / therfore if it be againſt the law of God &amp; againſt the law of nature to m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary our fathers ſiſters or ower mothers ſiſters / or els the wife of our fathers brother or our mothers brother / whoſe wifes be but of affinite to vs / &amp; th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at onely in the ſeconde degree: truly mych more it ſhulde be againſt nature to mary our brothers w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>idowe: for the nerer that thei cum to the ſtoke to be one fleſſhe &amp; blode: the more they ought to be forbi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>den: but our brother is more nerer vnto our father / as is aboue ſaid / than eyther owne vnkilles or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>untis. This ys now theſe perſones ſeconde reaſon the which I beſeke ye to note &amp; marke wel / &amp; ye ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hal ſe whate goodely lerning &amp; ſopheſtry thei ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we in it. For to perceyue this their Argument / ye muſt note how the huſbande / &amp; the wife be one fl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſhe
<pb facs="tcp:11164:65"/> &amp; blode: &amp; how the father &amp; the ſone be one fle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſhe &amp; blode. Firſt the huſband and the wife be one body in conſenting togither in their myndis &amp; wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>llis / &amp; in geuinge &amp; graunting eche of them to ot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>her the vſe of theyr bodies / and thus on this wyſe be the huſbande and the wife one body and blode / &amp; the father and the ſone be one fleſſhe and blode / by the reaſon that the ſone is engendered of the fath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers ſeade and ſubſtance by natural propagacion / &amp; nowe for to ſaye that he that marieth his brothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rs widowe marieth his fathers fleſſhe and blode / that is to ſaye the ſame fleſſhe and blode that ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of the widowes huſbandis father by generaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: is openly falſe. For the widow doith not come of the ſead and ſubſtance of hir huſbandis fathere nor no parte of hyr body &amp; blode comith of hyr huſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bandes fathers fleſſhe and blode: for to make hyr on this maner one fleſſhe and blode with hir fath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in lawe. And this theis Sophiſters muſte pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue yf they wolde haue their Argument good / for they muſt ſhewe that lyke as the father and the ſone is one fleſſhe and blode / ſo ys the ſone and his wife one fleſſhe and blode. Whiche ys falſe: for the ſone and the wife be one body after one maner / and the ſone and the father be one fleſſhe and blode af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a nother maner: as I haue ſhewid ye before / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d therfore their argument is nowght and doith not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hing conclude for their purpoſe.</p>
               <p>¶ Alſo the widowe is no more one body withe
<pb facs="tcp:11164:65"/> hyr huſbande that is deade: and therfore he that marieth the widowe doith not mary hir father in lawes fleſſhe and blode / the antecedent may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared thus: yf the widowe were ſtill one bodye w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ith hyr huſbande that is ded) ſhe might neuer ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry more: for ſhe might not graunte and gyue the vſe of hyr body to no man: for ſhe is one bodye ſtill with hyr huſbande that ys deid / and ſo than mig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ht ſhe neuer mary / which were the hereſy that ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulian was condempned in: wherfore it is falſe to ſaye that he that marieth his brothers widow / m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arieth his fathers fleſſhe and blode.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Arthermore of this theſe perſones re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſon / ye maye conclude: that the fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>her and the ſone may not mary y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and the doughter thus. For he t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hat takith and mariyth his fathers wyues dowghter / doith mary and take his fathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rs fleſſhe / and blode / for the father and his wife is one fleſſhe and blode: and the doughter / alſo is one fleſſhe and blode with hir mother and with hyr fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther in lawe / by the reaſon that he is one fleſſhe &amp; blode with her mother / and who ſo euer mariyth his fathers fleſſhe and blode: doith againſt the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we of nature / wherfore the ſone may not mary w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ith his mother in lawes dowghters: which is m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anifeſtly falſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:11164:66"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>F this reaſon ye may conclude that .ij. bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern may not mary .ij. ſiſtern / thus: he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> marye his brothers wiues ſiſter maryeth his brothers fleſſhe &amp; blode / for the brother &amp; hys wife be one fleſſhe &amp; blode / &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> brothers wife &amp; hyr ſiſter be one fleſſhe &amp; blode / &amp; the brothers wiues ſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſter is one fleſſhe &amp; blode with hir ſiſters huſban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis / &amp; he is one fleſſhe &amp; blode with his father: wh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfore his brother may not mary his wyues ſiſter for aſmuche as ſhe is his fathers fleſſhe &amp; blode / by reaſon that hyr ſiſter hath maried his brother / ye may ſe whate a Sophiſtical reaſon theſe perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ns bringe in greatly to their owne rebuke &amp; ſhame yf they had ony ſhame.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lſo this is manifeſtly falſe / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſaye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he which maryeth his fathers fleſſhe &amp; bl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ode / doith plainly againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law of nature for a manis ſone may mary by the law of nature his brothers doughters doughter / which is his f<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>athers fleſſhe &amp; blode. This no man wil deny wh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfore it is falſe to ſaye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he that marith his fathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rs fleſſhe &amp; blode / doith againſt the law of nature. Here now ye haue harde theſe perſones ſeconde r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſon / by the which they ſaid that thei wolde pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a man might not mary his brothers widowe &amp;c. &amp; thei haue nothinge done but ſhewed them ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lfe ſopheſtres / ful of wordes and empty of al treu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the and reaſon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:11164:66"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lſo in this their ſeconde reaſon / they ſaye yt is more againſt the law of God &amp; againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law of nature for a man to mary his broth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers widow &amp;c. than for a man to mary his aunte of eny ſyde / of this ſayng / it folowith y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> almyghty g<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>od in commaundinge the iues to marey their brot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hers widowes did commaunde / them to do that t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hing that was againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law of god &amp; agaynſt the law of nature: &amp; bonde them to the ſame vpon a g<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reat payne: &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was leſſe againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law of nature / he forbadde them: whiche is a commaund<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing &amp; a doyng againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> right ordre of reaſon. For reaſon willith y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the thing which is moſte euyll / ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>huld be moſt forbiden / &amp; of theis perſons ſaynge it folowith y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> almyghty God did contrary in the ol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de law / &amp; thus theſe perſons / deſpiſeth almighty Goddis commaunding &amp; doyng.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the .c. &amp; .xlj. leif of their boke / thei ſay that criſte nother did nothinge / nor ſayd no thing: but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he had takyn of his fath<hi rend="sup">r</hi>: nor brake no thinge of them: which his father commaundid / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d wolde haue doon. This they vnderſtande in thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were commaundid &amp; in ſuche as were forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> olde law: for they wold by this their ſayng conclude that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pope haith no power to diſpence / &amp; licence a man to mary his brothers wife a wido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we &amp;ce. for by cauſe thei ſaye / that ſuche mariage was forbiden in the olde law. And our ſauiour cr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſt did neuer breke nothing of them whiche his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:11164:67" rendition="simple:additions"/> commaundid / and wolde haue doon: wherfore the Pope that is Criſtes vicare / can not licence v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon ſuche mariage / vpon this their ſaynge / yt fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owith that the Iues be bounde ſtill to mary their brothers widowes lefte withoute yſſewe: and to circumciſion and to al the ceremonies and Iudicia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lls: For almighty God wolde that the Iues ſhul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de kepe them / and commaundid them to kepe theſe and owr ſauiour Criſte did neuer breke nothing of them which his father wolde haue kepte. Wherf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ore the Iues be now bounde to al theſe / ye and to al the hole law of Moyſes. This ys falſe and aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inſt the techinge of the Apoſtle where he ſayth, yf ye be circumciſed Criſt ſhal do yow no goode:<note place="margin">Gala. iiij. &amp;. v Gal. ij.</note> nor the keping of his commaundements ſhalbe noth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing profitable to yow. And agayne ſaynte Pol ſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth againſt Peter to his face / becauſe he wold y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gentils that were conuertid to kepe the ceremoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of the Iues. Here now ye may ſee that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtle did teche the people to breke &amp; to do contrary to the olde lawe: ye and ſo haith the churche decreid and made / that no man ſhal now mary his broth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers widow whiche is againſt the commaundment of the olde lawe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Vt for aſmuche as they ſaye that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ur ſauiour Criſt did neuer breke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o thinge of them which his father al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God commaundid and wold haue done: yow muſt note and vnd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erſtond
<pb facs="tcp:11164:67"/> that almighty God did commaunde cert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ayne thinges to be kepte for a certayne tyme / and in like maner certayn thinges he did forbide for a c<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ertain tyme / as the Iudicialles and ceremonies of the olde law he wolde haue ſuche as were comm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aundid to be done / the people to fulfill them and ke<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pe them: and ſuche as he forbade that the people ſhuld not do them / and yet for al this / almighty God did not commaunde the Iudiciallis nor cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies always to be kepte: but he willid that the Iues ſhulde kepe them vnto the tyme that it ſhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lde pleaſe him to ſende his ſone to take vpon him our nature: &amp; ſo to be very God and man our ſaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Criſt: and ſo to ſhewe vnto the worlde furt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>her his fathers wil and pleaſure / and what he w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olde haue all maner of people to kepe and obey fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me that tyme forewarde: and than our ſauiour cr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſt did diſſolue the Iudicialles and Ceremonies of the olde lawe / ſo that no man ſhulde be bounde to kepe them eny longer: nor put eny longer hope or truſte of ſaluacion in them.</p>
               <p>¶ And frome that tyme forth warde that alm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aner of people ſhulde put there hope of ſaluacion in beleuinge yn Almyghty God and yn Iuſtely kepinge ſuche Lawes and ſuche commaundment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is as almyghty God had ſent vnto them by hys ſone ower Sauioure Criſte. And thus owr Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uioure Criſte toke away after hys comynge the Iudicialles &amp; Ceremonyes of the olde lawe accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge vnto his fathers will and commandement.
<pb facs="tcp:11164:68"/> For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme of them was than exſpired / but nowe I muſte returne vnto theis perſons ſaynge which is this. It was commaundid by almyghty God in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> olde law that a man ſhulde not mary his br<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>others widow &amp;c. &amp; o<hi rend="sup">r</hi> ſauio<hi rend="sup">r</hi> criſt neuer brake noth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge of them / which almyghty God commaundid &amp; wolde haue done: wherfor the Pope can not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence vpon ſuche mariage. To this reaſon I anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maior of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reaſon is falſe: which is th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is / that almighty God commaunded in the olde l<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aw that no man ſhuld mary his brothers wife w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>idowe &amp;c. for yn y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> olde law almighty God did ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly commaunde the Iues always to mary th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eir brothers wiues widowes left &amp;c. &amp; that vpon a great payne / &amp; therfore it is falſe to ſaye that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God did commande in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> olde law that no man ſhulde mary his brothers widowe &amp;c. &amp; ſo th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfore is this falſe that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pope haue no power to diſpence vpon ſuche mariage: which theſe perſons wolde conclude vpon there falſe propoſicion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the .c. &amp; .xlv. leif of their boke theſe perſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons write that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leuitical prohibicion that a man ſhulde not mary his brothers wife a widow &amp;c. Thus thei muſt vnderſtand yt or ells it is not to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> purpoſe thoughe it was lymyted &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtrayned of almighty God in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Deuteronomi / yet for al that: bicauſe afterwarde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid reſtraynt w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as taken awaye of God him ſelf: by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> comyng of Cr ſt: here theſe perſons do not declare whate th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ey
<pb facs="tcp:11164:68"/> meane &amp; vnderſtande / by lymytynge &amp; reſtray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge of the leuiticall prohibicion / nor yet what t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hey wolde haue vnderſtanden by the taking aw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aye of the reſtraint / at the coming of o<hi rend="sup">r</hi> ſauiou<hi rend="sup">r</hi> cr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſt: but where as thei ſay y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the leuitical prohibicion that a man ſhuld not mary his brothers widowe &amp;c. was reſtraynide in the Deuteronomi / here the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe perſons ſay manifeſtly falſe: for as I haue ſaide oftin tymes / &amp; as ye haue harde many doctours ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aye / ye &amp; as the leuitical law it ſelf ſayth / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ther is no ſuche prohibicion there. &amp; therfore ther was no reſtraint made vpon that prohibicion: nor yet owr ſauiour Criſte did not at his cominge take awaye the reſtraynt: for ther was none to be taken away but in the Deuteronomi almyghty God did pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynly &amp; ſtreyghtely commaunde that the Iues ſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ulde mary always their brothers wyues widow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es left &amp;c. &amp; this confirmeth Iſichius ſayng:<note place="margin">in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. leui</note> that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law Deuteronomical did not onely comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to mary their brothers wiues widows: but it did alſo compell them ſo to mary. This therfor can be callid no reſtraynt: and thus all theſe perſones ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge ys falſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the ſame leif / theis deceyuers ſay / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> yf the Pope now a dayes coulde by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſacion / cauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a man might mary after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Deuteronomi his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wife which doith dye hauing no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne yſſewe for to reyſe vp ſede to his brother: witho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ute
<pb facs="tcp:11164:69"/> doughte he ſhulde make Criſten men at thys daye to folow the Iues ceremonyes &amp; ſuperſticion ſues / which the Pope can not do / no more than he can cauſe that we ſhulde kepe the Sabot daye: or that thei ſhulde be circunciſid. To this I anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re / that the Pope can not by diſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſacion cauſe a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to mary his brothers widow &amp;c. as the Iues in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> olde law maryed theirs. Nor the Pope doith not li<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cence a man to mary his brothers widowe after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> facion &amp; maner: but the Pope doith licence &amp; diſpen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a Criſten man may mary his brothers widow as a kynge or a prince to mary his brothers wido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we / to be meane that queytnes &amp; peace may be kep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te betwene realme &amp; realme: &amp; for to continew loue &amp; frendeſhip betwene Criſten princes / &amp; for other ſuche reaſonable &amp; profitable cauſes concerning the comyn welthe of Criſtendome / &amp; thus for theis / &amp; ſuche cauſes the Pope doith &amp; maye diſpence that a man may mary his brothers widowe &amp;c. &amp; not af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter the maner of the Iues: &amp; therfore theis perſons bringe yn a thing that no man will deny / and yet it is nothing for their purpoſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the .cliij. leif of their boke / theſe perſones ſaye that like as a man may frely fulfil h<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is purpoſe of a more holyer lyuynge (the ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ayng nay &amp; frowarde forbiddinge of his indiſcrete prelate notwithſtanding) euen ſo it is yn mariage that if a mans conſciens moue him to diuorſe: th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at he dyuorſe hym ſelf though the church ſay con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary.
<pb facs="tcp:11164:69"/> Here now ye may ſe &amp; perceyue theis peſtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent perſons vngracious &amp; maliciouſe entent: &amp; w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hat thei counſail / &amp; wolde haue done (y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> is to ſaye) a man to diuorſe him ſelfe / &amp; to forſake his wife yf his conſcience moue him to diuorſe) without eny fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rther profe or ſhewing of eny iuſt cauſe: &amp; to mary where yt pleſid him thoughe the churche ſayd the contrary: which is clerly againſt al reaſon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lſo by this their ſaynge yowe may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue that theſe perſones wolde vtterly deſtroye the bliſſed ſacrament of matrim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ony. For by this meane &amp; waye: euery man as of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten as he wold chaunge his conſcience to diuorſe / ſo often he might chaunge his wife / ye &amp; the wife hyr huſband / without ſhewinge of eny other profe or cauſe / &amp; without eny maner of ſentence &amp; iugement of the churche: ye &amp; thowgh the church ſaid &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundide the contrary / &amp; ſo by this / ſhulde the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of matrimony be deſtroid. Here ye may ſe what peſtlent perſons theſe be / whiche haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piled this boke that I anſwere to.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Vrthermore theyr compariſon and ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude: wherby they wolde proue that a man maye diuorſe hym ſelfe frome hys wyfe by hys conſcience / thowghe the Churche ſaye contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rey / ys openly falſe. Fore thowghe yt be ſo t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hat a Prieſte / be mouede yn hys mynde to be
<pb facs="tcp:11164:70"/> a religious man / may frely fulfil his purpoſe of a more holier lyuinge (notwithſtanding y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nay of his indiſcrete prelate) yet it doith not folowe / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euen ſo yt is in mariage: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> yf a mans conſcience moue him to diuorſe / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he may diuorſe him ſelf &amp; forſake hys wife / &amp; mary anoth<hi rend="sup">r</hi> / thowghe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church ſay cont<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rary: This caſe is not like the oth<hi rend="sup">r</hi>: firſt forbicau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a prieſt which goith to religion for a more holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er lyuing / may fulfil his godly purpoſe lefully (n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>otwithſtanding y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> frowarde / forbidding of his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcrete prelate) for aſmuche as the prieſt beyng at libertye / &amp; doing no wronge to no perſon by the rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon of his going to religion: but ſeruith almighty God better. Thus he may fulfil his godly purpo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe thoughe his vndiſcreite prelaite ſaye contrary / but ſo may not a man that is maryed / diuorſe hym ſelf whan his conſcience mouith him to diuorſe / for bicauſe the maried man is not at libertie / For he is bounde to continew with his wife accordinge to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawes of matrimony during al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme of his lyfe / nor he can not departe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his wife for to mary an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>oth<hi rend="sup">r</hi>: while y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his wife is a lyue. Wherfore there is no conſcience that can helpe a maryed man in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ater of diuorſe / excepte he can manifeſtly proue ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me iuſte cauſe befor y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church: that his mariage ys not good. And than he muſt abyde &amp; ſtonde to the churches iugement &amp; determinacion. And therfore this is falſe / to ſay that lyke as a prieſt may for a more holier lyuinge / fulful his purpoſe (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the forbiddinge or nay of his vndiſcreite
<pb facs="tcp:11164:70"/> prelate) euen ſo it is in mariage / that if a mans co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nſcience moue him to diuorſe: that he diuorſe hym ſelf thowghe the church ſay contrary. Nowe here ye may ſe what thinge theſe perſones wolde haue done / and after what maner.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow for to come to an ende / theſe deceyu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers ſay in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preface of their boke: that the vniuerſites wil put for the reaſons of more waight ſhortly to al the worlde than theſe perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ns haue ſhewid in theyr boke: ſewerly ſo had thu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſities nede to do. For theis perſons (as ye ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue ſene) haue brought noone but ſuche as be abho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>minable / ſhamful &amp; falſe / but the vniuerſites aft<hi rend="sup">r</hi> due ordyr a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d reaſon / ſhulde a put for the firſt theyr reaſons: &amp; than their determinacions / &amp; that ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in determininge a mater or a pointe of our fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th / &amp; I ſuppoſe ſo they wolde haue done / yf thei h<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ad determined the trowth / but for as myche as t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hey haue determined that thinge that is very fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe / to be trew: therfore thei put forth no reaſons w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ith their determinacions: nor thei can none fynde to put forth / why they haue thus determined: w<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herfor I breuely conclude / that the vniuerſities h<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aue determined falſly in this caſe that I haue ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of / &amp; that this propoſicion is falſe / that yt ys a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gainſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law of God &amp; againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law of nature for a man to mary his brothers wife a widow left &amp;c</p>
               <p>¶ Now ye haue harde parte of theis perſons b<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſphemy
<pb facs="tcp:11164:71"/>
/ parte of their errors / parte of their ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mful lies / &amp; falſnes / &amp; beſide al this ye may perce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yue how theſe vngracious perſons haue geuen gr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eat occaſion to deſtroy kyndenes &amp; amite among c<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſten princes / &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thei ſowe for loue / hatered &amp; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde / &amp; alſo ye may perceyue what great myſcheif theſe perſons with their labour / counſell / opinion / &amp; boke haue begun <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ye &amp; how mych more myſcheyf they wold do / yf thei might bringe their maliciou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe purpoſe to effecte: ye may lykwiſe ꝑceyue in wh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at confuſion (with their falſe opinion) thei wold b<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring princes concerning their mariages. And final<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly what a ſiſme &amp; a diuiſion (with their opinion) thei haue ſtered vp in criſtendom / for by their opin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion / thei affirme y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al criſtes church haith thus m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>any yeres erred in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faith in diſpenſing in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſte &amp; ſecond degre of affinite &amp; conſanguinite / al this fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth of theſe vngracious perſons falſe opinion / with mych more than I reherſe / wherfor let no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iuge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in my anſwer I rebuke them / with yre and paſſion: but rath<hi rend="sup">r</hi> I had cauſe to reproue them ſhar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pelyer for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thei haue ſo hiely offendid almighty g<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>od: ye a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d they cauſe many ſo to do / wherfor theis euil perſons ar wel worthy rebuke &amp; reproue. o<hi rend="sup">r</hi> ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>auio<hi rend="sup">r</hi> criſt vehemently rebuked y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> falſe ſcribes ph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ariſeis and falſe teachers / bicauſe thei offendid god &amp; taught other ſo to do / alſo Iohn bap. reproued &amp; ſharply rebuked falſe prophetes &amp; teachers / ſo did Pol &amp; Iohn in theyr piſtils / Hierom / Ambros / a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſten &amp; many oth<hi rend="sup">r</hi> holy fathers: for nothing offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth
<pb facs="tcp:11164:71"/> God more than teachers of falſe doctrine / nor ther is non ſo incurable a peſtilence / nor ſo hurtful to mans ſowle / as is falſe doctrine / yf it be accept &amp; beleued / wherfor ye may perceyue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I had a iuſte cauſe to rebuke &amp; reproue theſe vngracious perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ns y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> haue ſet forth this boke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I anſwer to. For t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hey teche falſe doctrine &amp; wold haue yt to be accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te &amp; beleued: &amp; thoughe I haue not ſo ſubſtancially &amp; profoundly anſwered here in euery pointe / as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther better lernyd men parauentur ſhal do heraft<hi rend="sup">r</hi> yet for all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> my conſcience wold not ſuffer me to h<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>old my peace / but compellid me to offer with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poor widow a farthing of my lerninge to the honour of almighty God. Wherfor I will mekely beſeke ye to accepte this my anſwere / my zele / and will / in good wurth: as I truſt he doith / for whoſe ſake a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d cauſe I toke vpon me to make this anſwer / whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ch is owr ſauiour criſt: to whome be gyuen all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and laude. AMEN.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>The lefe / pagyn / &amp; lyne. the fautes. thame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts B. i. Pagi. i. Lin. i. almighty almighty god H. i. Pag. i. Lin. viij. ys it it ys N. i. Pag. ij. Lin. viij. other oth N. iij. Pag. i. Lin. xv. hath no pow<hi rend="sup">r</hi> / hath power.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Imprinted at Luneberge the yere of ower Lorde God. M.D.XXXII. in Maye</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
